اَعُوْذُ بِاللهِ مِنَّ الشِّيْطَانِ الرَّجِيْمِ۝ بِسْمِ اللهِ الرَّحْمَانِ الرَّحِيْمَ۝
اَلْحَمْدُ لله وَالصَّلَاةُ وَالسَّلَامُ عَلى سَيِّدِنَا محمد وَعَلَى اَلِهِ وَصَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ
اللهم الشرح الصدرك وارنا ألحق يا أرحم الراحمين ،
رَبَّنَا آتِنَا فِي الدُّنْيَا حَسَنَةً وَفِي الْآخِرَةِ حَسَنَةً وَقِنَا عَذَابَ النَّارِ
The next section is the longest continuous section, where Shaikh(شيخ) Ibn Nuhas(إبن نُحاس) talks.
This is an advice to the ones, who stay behind.
It’s a wonderful Naseeha(نَصيحة) that he gives to the ones, who miss out on Jihad(جهاد) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله).
He says: Oh, you who have neglected Jihad(جهاد) and stayed away from the path of success.
You have put yourself in the position of exclusion from the mercy of Allah.
You have deprived yourself from the greatest reward.
What is it that caused you to stay behind?
Why haven't you joined the ranks of the Mujahideen(مجاهدين)?
Why are you holding back your soul and your wealth?
It must be one of the following reasons.
1) The desire to live a long life.
2) The attachment to family, wealth, or friends.
3)The desire to do more good deeds before fighting Jihad(جهاد).
4) The love of a beautiful wife.
5) Your position of power or love of a comfortable lifestyle.
Nothing else could be holding you back.
It must be one of the above mentioned reasons that is keeping you away from Allah.
Can’t you hear the call of Allah directed at you:
يا أَيُّهَا الَّذينَ آمَنوا ما لَكُم إِذا قيلَ لَكُمُ انفِروا في سَبيلِ اللَّهِ اثّاقَلتُم إِلَى الأَرضِ ۚ
أَرَضيتُم بِالحَياةِ الدُّنيا مِنَ الآخِرَةِ ۚ
فَما مَتاعُ الحَياةِ الدُّنيا فِي الآخِرَةِ إِلّا قَليلٌ۞
Oh, you have believed! What is the matter with you that, when you are told to go forth in the cause of Allah,
you adhere heavily to the earth.
Are you satisfied with the life of this world rather than the Hereafter?
But what is the enjoyment of worldly life compared to the hereafter except a very little.
Listen carefully to how I respond to each and every one of the causes, that are holding you back from Jihad(جهاد),
you will then come to realize that you are deprived,
and you would learn that it is nothing but yourself and Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ)
that is preventing you from Jihad(جهاد);
1) Number One: The desire to live longer:
In the name of Allah fearlessness does not decrease your life.
And cowardice does not increase it.
Allah says:
وَلِكُلِّ أُمَّةٍ أَجَلٌ ۖ
فَإِذا جاءَ أَجَلُهُم لا يَستَأخِرونَ ساعَةً ۖ وَلا يَستَقدِمونَ۞
And for every nation is a specified term.
So when their time has come, they will not remain behind an hour, nor will they proceed it.
This is in Al-Araf(ألأعراف) Verse 34.
And Allah says:
وَلَن يُؤَخِّرَ اللَّهُ نَفسًا إِذا جاءَ أَجَلُها ۚ وَاللَّهُ خَبيرٌ بِما تَعمَلونَ۞
But never will Allah delay a soul when it's time has come.
And Allah is acquainted with what you do.
And that’s in Al-Munafiqoon(ألمنافقون) verse 11.
And Allah says:
كُلُّ نَفسٍ ذائِقَةُ المَوتِ ۖ ثُمَّ إِلَينا تُرجَعونَ۞
Every soul will taste death, then to us, you will be returned.
And this is in Al-Ankabut(ألعنكبوت), Verse 57.
And then he says: Oh, you have deceived yourself!
Remember that during death, there's agony and pain.
And on the Day of Judgment, there's great fear.
Do you remember that a Shaheed(شَهِيد) is spared from all of this.
He does not feel the pain of death, except like a sting of an insect.
My brother, why miss out on this opportunity.
And then after death, you would be spared from the punishment of the grave.
You will not go through the questioning of the angels in the grave.
And you will be tranquil on the day of judgment, when everybody else is horrified.
After your death your soul will be in the Inside of birds flying in paradise.
Can you see the difference between dying a natural death and being a Shaheed(شَهِيد)?
2) Number two: Attachment to family:
If what prevents you from Jihad(جهاد) is family, wealth and friends, Then; Allah says:
وَما أَموالُكُم وَلا أَولادُكُم بِالَّتي تُقَرِّبُكُم عِندَنا زُلفىٰ
بِالَّتي تُقَرِّبُكُم عِندَنا زُلفىٰ إِلّا مَن آمَنَ وَعَمِلَ صالِحًا
فَأُولٰئِكَ لَهُم جَزاءُ الضِّعفِ بِما عَمِلوا وَهُم فِي الغُرُفاتِ آمِنونَ۞
And it is not your wealth or your children that brings you nearer to us in position,
but it is by being one, who has believed and done righteousness.
So these things don't really bring you closer to Allah.
اعلَموا أَنَّمَا الحَياةُ الدُّنيا لَعِبٌ وَلَهوٌ وَزينَةٌ وَتَفاخُرٌ بَينَكُم
وَتَفاخُرٌ بَينَكُم وَتَكاثُرٌ فِي الأَموالِ وَالأَولادِ ۖ
كَمَثَلِ غَيثٍ أَعجَبَ الكُفّارَ نَباتُهُ ثُمَّ يَهيجُ فَتَراهُ مُصفَرًّا
ثُمَّ يَهيجُ فَتَراهُ مُصفَرًّا ثُمَّ يَكونُ حُطامًا ۖ
وَفِي الآخِرَةِ عَذابٌ شَديدٌ وَمَغفِرَةٌ مِنَ اللَّهِ وَرِضوانٌ ۚ
وَمَا الحَياةُ الدُّنيا إِلّا مَتاعُ الغُرورِ۞
Know that the life of this world is, but amusement
and diversion, and adornment and boasting to one another,
and competition in the increase of wealth and children.
Like the example of a rain whose plant growth pleases the tillers,
then it dries and you see it turned yellow, then it becomes debris.
And in the Hereafter is a severe punishment and forgiveness from Allah and approval.
And what is the worldly life except the enjoyment of delusion.
That’s Surah Al-Hadid(سورة ألحديد) verse 20.
The Messenger of Allah said:
And the area under a whip, or under your foot in Paradise is better than the world and everything in it.
That's in Bukhari(بخاريْ).
So does it make sense to leave this vast Kingdom in paradise for the sake of your family,
who in a short while will be among the dead.
A family that might Express towards you animosity, bad behavior or jealousy.
If you are wealthy, they love you.
If you're broke, they forsake you.
One day they are with you, and the next day against you.
In the end, on the day of judgment, they will leave you alone,
and they would hold you accountable for even the size of a grain.
They would all desire that they would be saved on that day,
even if it is you that is going to hell fire.
Allah سبحانه تعالى says that, on the day of judgment, a person would wish to sacrifice
their wife, their children, their parents, their tribe and everyone in the earth,
if it's going to save them from hellfire.
3) Number Three: Love of wealth: If it is your wealth that is keeping you behind,
then how can it do so, when you know that it will eventually leave you?
See, the problem here is that you don't want to leave your wealth,
but your wealth is going to leave you.
So why not leave it and get the Ajr(أجْر), rather than be forced, for it to leave you?
And because of this wealth, you will be asked on the Day of Judgment: How did you make it and how did you spend it?
You will be asked these two questions on a day that would make a child gray headed, a day of horror.
The Messenger of Allah said: The poor Muslims will proceed the rich in Paradise
by half a day, 500 years.
Allah says:
إِنَّما أَموالُكُم وَأَولادُكُم فِتنَةٌ ۚ
وَاللَّهُ عِندَهُ أَجرٌ عَظيمٌ۞
Your wealth and your children are, but a trial.
And Allah has with Him a great reward.
At-Taghabagun(ألتغابن) Verse 15.
Rasool Allah ﷺ says in a Hadith(حديث) that the poor are among Al-Muhajiroon(ألمهاجرون).
There are many poor among Al-Muhajiroon(ألمهاجرون), they came out from Makkah.
They had to leave everything behind them.
Some of them were originally wealthy, but they became broke.
Hijrah(هجرة) wasn't a very easy thing.
They had to leave their wealth behind.
For example, Suhaib
Al-Rumi(صهيب الرومي).
Suhaib Al-Rumi(صهيب الرومي) is Roman, and he was a slave in Makkah.
But he did business in Makkah, and he became wealthy.
He accumulated a lot of wealth, when he was in Makkah.
He became Muslim.
And when he went out in Hijrah(هجرة), some of the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) pursued him.
And he stood on a hill and he took an arrow from his quiver and he pointed towards him, and he said:
You know that I'm among the best archers in Makkah.
I'm going to empty my quiver in you If you don't leave me alone.
Then he said:
أتَيْتَنَا سَولُوكً فَسَارَ لَكَ بَيَنَ مالً وَاَهْل
They said: You came to us in Makkah broke.
And you lived among us, and accumulated wealth.
Now you want to leave and take your wealth with you.
We're not going to let you go with your money.
And I think in this story is a stark warning for Muslims, who are living in the West.
Maybe one day the same thing will happen.
You'll be told you came here broke and poor, and you became wealthy among us.
You can’t just leave and take your money with you.
So they told Suhaib(صهيب): Give us your money.
He said: Fine!
You will find my money in such and such place in Makkah.
So he ransomed himself for them by giving them his wealth.
Suhaib(صهيب) arrived in Madina and as soon as Rasool Allah ﷺ saw him, he told him;
ربَيهَ ألبَية أبى يحيى
What a profitable trade, Abu Yahya(أبويحيى)!”
Without Suhaib(صهيب) telling him the story,
the news was already with the Rasool Allah ﷺ and he told him: That was a profitable deal.
You lost all of your money- and then he’s congratulated that it's a good deal,
because it's really a good deal.
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ will give you more.
So there are many poor among Al-Muhajireen(مهاجرين).
Rasool Allah ﷺ says: These poor Muhajireen(مهاجرين) are going to knock on the gates of Jannah(جنة).
So the angels are going to open the gates and say: What are you doing here?
Isn’t the day of judgment still going on?
The Hisab(حساب), proceedings of the Hisab(حساب) is still going on,
and these Muhajireen(مهاجرين) are already knocking on the gates, they want to get in.
So the angels are telling them? Didn’t you have to go through the reckoning?
So the Al-Muhajiroon(ألمهاجرون) said: We would be reckoned for what?
All what we used to do, while we were living was carrying our swords on our shoulders and fight Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله),
what are we going to be asked about?
We had no businesses, because you see …
لا تزول قدما عبد يوم القيامة حتى يسأل عن أربع
You are not going to move your feet,
your feet are not gonna move from the tracks on the Day of Judgment, until you're asked four questions;
About your life, about your youth.
And then the other two questions are relating to what? Money.
How did you make money? And how did you spend it?
So two questions relate to money, and that's what's going to hold people behind.
That's what it's gonna delay them.
Because you're going to be asked about each and every penny that you made, and that you spent.
So these Al-Muhajiroon(ألمهاجرون) said: We didn't have any money to be asked about.
We're carrying our swords…
على عواتقنا حدنا وحدنا في سبيل الله
We died for the sake of Allah. So what are we going to be asked about?
So the angel will tell them: You're welcome, come in!
- while everybody else is still going to the Hisab(حساب).
4) Number four: Love of your children and caring for them:
Is it because you care for them?
Well, Allah is more careful for them than you.
Didn’t He care for them while they were in the darkness of their mother's womb?
How can such a child prevent you from Jihad(جهاد), when if he is young, you are concerned.
And when they grow old, you are still concerned.
You are concerned about them when they are healthy, and you're concerned about them when they're sick.
If you discipline them, they revolt against you.
If you advise them, they hate you.
And after all of your care for them, when you grow old, they forsake you,
and you still see them as a blessing.
Get them out of your mind and hand them over to the One, Who created them.
And trust Allah in their provisions as He trust them in yours.
How can you acknowledge that Allah is the One, Who manages the affairs of the heavens and earth,
and you don't trust him with the provisions of your children?
I mean, don't we all acknowledge that Allah is the One, Who is running the affairs of the universe?
Don't we believe that Allah is the One, Who is providing the Rizq(رزق)
for every fish in the sea and every animal on the land and every bird in the air?
Don’t we believe that Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ is the One, Who has created and is sustaining the universe,
this huge universe?
And then we don’t trust Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ with the provisions of our children.
In the name of Allah, you have no authority over the harm or benefit that befalls them, or even yourself.
You have no control even over your own life or theirs.
You cannot even add a day to their life.
One day you would be dead and then you would leave your children, orphans behind you.
Then you would say: I wish I were with the martyrs,
and the response would be, now it's too late. Allah says:
يا أَيُّهَا النّاسُ اتَّقوا رَبَّكُم وَاخشَوا يَومًا لا يَجزي والِدٌ عَن وَلَدِهِ
وَلا مَولودٌ هُوَ جازٍ عَن والِدِهِ شَيئًا ۚ
إِنَّ وَعدَ اللَّهِ حَقٌّ ۖ
فَلا تَغُرَّنَّكُمُ الحَياةُ الدُّنيا وَلا يَغُرَّنَّكُم بِاللَّهِ الغَرورُ۞
Oh mankind! Fear your Lord, and fear a day when no father will avail his son,
nor will a son avail his father at all.
Indeed the promise of Allah is true,
so let not the worldly life delude you,
and be not deceived about Allah by the deceiver, Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ).
And this is Luqman(لُقمان) verse 33.
Now if your child is among the successful people of paradise,
then you will be reunited with them in Jannah(جنة)
and if he is among the losers, then why wait?
Let the separation be from now.
If you truly care for your child, then die as a Shaheed(شَهِيد),
you would  then be able to appeal for 70 of your family-members.
So what are you waiting for?
Now Umar Bin Abdul Aziz(عمربن عبدالعزيز), when he was in Sakarat-Ul-Maut(سكرات الموت), when he was dying,
Umar Bin Abdul Aziz(عمربن عبدالعزيز) made things strict on his family, very strict.
So when he was dying, his relatives, you know Bannu Umayyah(بَنُواُمَيَّة) they are all living a very high class life,
and now the Khalifah(خليفه) and his wife and children are living this difficult life.
You know it's like they didn't belong to the family.
Fatima Bint Abdul Malik(فاطمه بنت عبدالملك), the wife of Umar Bin Abdul Aziz(عمربن عبدالعزيز), was brought up in a house of Khilafah(خِلَافَه).
Her father was a Khalifah(خليفه), Abdul Malik Bin Marwan(عبدالملك بن مروان ),
three of her brothers were Khulafa(خلفاء),
Suleiman Bin Abdul Malik(سليمان بن عبدالملك), Hisham Bin Abdul Malik(هشام بن عبدالملك) and Waleed bin Abdul Malik(وليدبن عبدالملك),
and she's a wife of a Khalifah(خليفه), Umar Bin Abdul Aziz(عمربن عبدالعزيز) surrounded by Khulafa(خلفاء) from all over.
Nevertheless, he took all of her jewelry and he gave it out to Sadaqah(صدقة)
and he would have her wear very simple clothes.
So Bannu Umayyah(بَنُواُمَيَّة) were, putting pressure on the Khalifah(خليفه). Why are you doing this?
So they came to him. And obviously they knew that he's not going to change his ways.
So when he was dying, they came to him to at least convince him to do something for his kids.
So they told him: You don't have anything to leave behind for your children, nothing.
At least give them something.
And it's Halal(حلال), you don't have to steal anything,
give them like you're giving the rest of the Ummah(امة), I mean there is so much wealth in the Ummah(امة).
They're pay every Muslim a salary for no work.
Everybody was receiving a salary because there was so much to hand out.
So they're telling him, he needs something for his children.
Umar Bin Abdul Aziz(عمربن عبدالعزيز) said: Bring them, bring my children.
So they brought them and they were all lined up in front of him, all of them.
And you know before death, it's a very difficult time,
you know, Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ) can come to you and make you feel sorry for them.
So they were all lined up in front of him wearing very simple clothes.
And then he looked at them and he said: My son is either is a Mo'min(مؤمن) or Fajir(فاجر),
my children are either going to be a Mo'min(مؤمن) or a corrupt person.
He said: If they are a Mo'min(مؤمن), believers, Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ is going to give them Rizq(رزق),
and if my son grows up to become corrupt, I don't want to support him in his corruption.
And he decided not to leave them anything behind, and he died without leaving them anything.
The narrator of the story said:
I've  later on seen the sons of Umar Bin Abdul Aziz(عمربن عبدالعزيز) when they grew old.
Every one of them was a millionaire. And every one of them was Salih(صالح), everyone was righteous.
Put your trust in Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ, it is better for you than what you think is right.
فوضع امورك الى الله
Put your affairs in the hands of Allah and let Him manage your affairs for you.
Rasool Allah ﷺ used to say in the Dua(دُعَا),
اللهم لا تكلني الى نفسي طرفة عين
O Allah don't put my affairs in my hands even if even a blink of an eye,
even for as long as a blink of an eye, keep my affairs in your hands.
5) Your friends, Number 5): If you are unable to leave behind your friends and acquaintances,
then remember the day of judgment.
On that day friends are enemies, except the righteous among them,
so if your friends are not righteous then we don't want to be with them today.
Because tomorrow they will turn against you.
But if they are righteous, then Allah will unite you together in a better place, than this.
Allah سبحانه تعالى says:
وَنَزَعنا ما في صُدورِهِم مِن غِلٍّ إِخوانًا عَلىٰ سُرُرٍ مُتَقابِلينَ۞
And we will remove whatever is in their breasts of resentment.
So they will be brothers on thrones facing each other.
وَنَزَعْنَا مَا فِى صُدُورِهِم مِّنْ غِلٍّ إِخْوَٰنًا عَلَىٰ سُرُرٍ مُّتَقَٰابِلِينَ۞
And this is Al Hijr(ألحجر) verse 47
6) Power and prestige:
You might be staying behind the ranks of the Mujahideen(مجاهدين)
because you fear the loss of what you have established so far in your life in terms of position, power, and prestige.
This position you're holding, how many hands did it passed through until it reached you?
So if this position left them, it would one day leave you.
Your power is temporary, and your prestige will soon be forgotten.
Your position, power and prestige are keeping you away from the path of paradise.
Now the lowest person in paradise will own 10 times the whole world  and everything in it.
This is the power and position of the lowest person in paradise.
It’s the greater than that of the greatest king of this world.
Nothing in this world is the free of contamination.
The position you are holding has its fair share of disappointments.
In order to win power and positions you will have to struggle,
you will win enemies and lose friends.
You will suffer pain and defeats along the way.
Paradise is free all of that, Allah says:
جَنّاتُ عَدنٍ يَدخُلونَها وَمَن صَلَحَ مِن آبائِهِم وَأَزواجِهِم وَذُرِّيّاتِهِم ۖ
وَالمَلائِكَةُ يَدخُلونَ عَلَيهِم مِن كُلِّ بابٍ۞
سَلامٌ عَلَيكُم بِما صَبَرتُم ۚ فَنِعمَ عُقبَى الدّارِ۞
Gardens of  perpetual residence,
they will enter them with whoever were righteous among their fathers, their spouses and their descendants.
And the angels will enter upon them from every gate saying:
Peace be upon you for what you patiently endure.
And excellent is the final home.
Al-Ra'ad(ألرَّعد) Twenty three and Twenty four(23-24).
Now, he talks about the contamination of this world.
Jannah(جنة) is different than Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) in four areas:
Number 1)
الدنيا فانية والجنة باقية
This world is temporary and Akhirah(آخرة) is permanent.
Allah says about Duniyah(دُنِيَّا)
متاع الغرور
And Allah says about Jannah(جنة),
والاخرة خير وابقى
Akhirah(آخرة) is better and everlasting.
Number 2) There's a difference in quantity.
Number 3) There is a difference in quality.
Number 4) Everything in Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) is contaminated.
And everything in Akhirah(آخرة) is pure.
Number 1) Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) is temporary and Akhirah(آخرة) is permanent.
How long are you going to live in Duniyah(دُنِيَّا)?
I was watching in Al-Jazeera(ألجزيرة) and in the news strip it said that the oldest man in the world has passed away
in Japan at the age of 114, that's the oldest, 114.
How long will you live in Akhirah(آخرة)? Infinity.
Now if we want to make a ratio Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) to Akhirah(آخرة).
What do you do to make a ratio?
You divide Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) on Akhirah(آخرة).
So 114 divided by infinity, what's the answer?
Yani(يعني) Math tells us that it's zero. Nothing!
There isn't even a ratio.
But Rasool Allah ﷺ was more generous than that. He said: If this world was worth a wing of a mosquito,
but then you can notice that Rasool Allah ﷺ said: One wing so the mosquito can't even fly.
He didn't even say two wings.
So Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) is nothing. Worthless !
Number two. Quantity.
Musa عليه السّلام asked Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ, what's the lowest level in Jannah(جنة)
and this Hadith(حديث) is in Muslim(مسلم).
There's another Hadith(حديث). Rasool Allah ﷺ talks about the lowest level in Jannah(جنة), they're quite similar.
Rasool Allah ﷺ says: The last man to come out of Hellfire, he will come out of hellfire,
and just because he came out of Hellfire, he’s not in Jannah(جنة) yet, he is so happy.
He will say: Oh Allah, You have given me something that you have not given to any of Your creation.
He doesn’t what is going on in Jannah(جنة)? He just thinks that being out from hellfire is good enough,
not good enough, he thinks that is the best.
But then he see a tree in the horizon.
Now this is the desolate land between Jahannum(جَهَّنَّم) and Jannah(جنة).
So he see a tree in the horizon.
So he says: O Allah, can You allow me to please go under that tree,
so that I can drink from the water and eat from its fruits and enjoy its shade.
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ tells him, You can go!
So he goes under the tree.
But then, when he get there he sees another tree.
Now he has already told Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ before that I am not going to ask for anything more.
He said: that’s all what I want! Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ tells him: Didn’t you promise that you don’t ask for anything else.
Because he said: I want to go next to that tree.
Allah told him: You promise that you're not going to ask for anything else.
He said: O Allah this is the last time,
I promise, I am not ask for anything more.
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ tells him: You can go. He gets there, and he sees a better tree.
He says: O Allah, Let me go under that tree, so that I can drink from its water and eats its fruit, Allah will tell him:
Son of Adam(آدم), didn’t you promise that you’re not going ask for anything more?
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
وهو لأنه يرى ما لا صبرله عليه
The man is seeing something, and he has no patience,
he cannot hold back.
So he keeps on breaking his promise again and again.
The third time Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ tells him: You promise!
You are not going to ask for anything else.
He said: I promise this is the last time.
So he goes under another tree but then when gets under that the tree what does he see.
He sees the walls of Jannah(جنة).
He says: O Allah, I don’t want to go in. Just let me sit under that wall, just sit under that wall.
And you see the thing is, because it is getting closer to Jannah(جنة), even though he's not Jannah(جنة) yet,
because we are getting closer to Jannah(جنة), even though it's outside of Jannah(جنة).
The Barakaat(بركات) of Jannah(جنة) are even influencing  this waste-land,
and the further he gets away from hell fire the better it becomes.
Because hellfire kills everything and Jannah(جنة) gives life to everything.
So Allah tells him: Alright go under the walls of Jannah(جنة).
He goes under the walls of Jannah(جنة) and when he gets there. Rasool Allah ﷺ said:
He starts hearing the conversion of the  people of Jannah(جنة),
And that’s when he Just cannot keep his promise.
Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله)! He doesn’t even  see the people of Jannah(جنة),
he just hears, he just hears their conversion
and that in itself drives him crazy,
just their voice.
He says: O Allah please allow me to go in, just get through the gates, just allow me to go in.
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ tell him: O Son of Adam(آدم) what will please you?
Would you be  pleased: If I give you the equivalent of the entire world and everything in it.
He will say: O Allah, Yes! I would be pleased.
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ will tell him, I will give you that, an equivalent to it,
and equivalent to it, and equivalent to it. So five times the earth, and everything in it.
And then he says, Oh Allah, that's enough! That's enough!
He's trying to interrupt Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ and tell him. That's enough!
And Allah is adding more and he's saying Oh Allah,
رضيتُ يا رب، رضيتُ يا رب
O Allah I am please, I'm satisfied. I don't want anything more,
until Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ gives him, 10 times the world and everything in it,
and then Allah tells him and then I will give you on top of that,
whatever will satisfy your eyes and please your heart.
That is the lowest level in Jannah(جنة), the absolute lowest, 10 times this world and everything in it.
And this belongs to a man who spent a long term in Hellfire,
it's belong to him. What about the people who will go straight to Jannah(جنة) what will Allah give them?
So, when Musa(موسى) asked Allah, What about the highest level of Jannah(جنة),
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ tells Musa(موسى).
أُولَئِكَ الَّذِينَ أرَدْتُ غَرَسْتُ كَرامَتَهُمْ بيَدِي،
For those I'm gonna plan their honor in paradise with my own hands
and for those there’s something special and then Rasool Allah ﷺ says,
فيها مال عين الراعئة ،،
وَلَا رضو سَمِعَت ،
ولَمْ يَخْطُرْ علَى قَلْبِ بَشَرٍ
In Jannah(جنة) are things, an eye has never seen, an ear has never heard and a heart has never imagined.
You want to try to imagine as much as you can!
You are not even going to get close that what is in Jannah(جنة).
So that’s the quantity. In terms of quality.
Rasool Allah ﷺ says:
مَوْضِعُ سَوْطٍ في الجَنَّةِ، خَيْرٌ مِنَ الدُّنْيا وما فيها،
In Bukhari(بخاريْ), Rasool Allah ﷺ says:
The area under your whip in paradise, is better than the world and everything in it.
How big is a whip? One foot by one inch?
So a piece of real estate in Jannah(جنة), one foot by one inch, costs more than the entire Earth.
Now you're given 10 times the size of the earth.
So the numbers are now getting into the astronomical area,
so we have to use light years because zeros won't do it anymore.
And then the fourth difference is contamination.
Everything in Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) is contaminated.
Whatever pleasure you have in Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) is contaminated and whatever pleasure exists in Aakhirah(آخِرة) is pure.
In Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) according to what the scholars of the Salaf(سلف) say,
that the highest form of pleasure that Allah has given In Duniyah(دُنِيَّا),
is what happens between a man and his wife.
Ibn Al Jawzi(إبن ألجوزي) talks about this, and says:
If one would think about that. You would see how contaminated it is!
And then he gives an example.
He says when a man would kiss his wife,
if one would just make Tafakkur(تفَّكُّر) on what happens and think about it.
They would realize, how such a thing without the Shahwa(شهوة) that Allah سبحانه تعالى put no human being would do.
If it wasn’t for the desire that Allah سبحانه تعالى has put, for the purpose of reproduction
in the human race, no human being would do that.
And if you think about for example, the Shahwa(شهوة) that Allah has given you to eat,
you have that urge to eat and it's one of the pleasures that you have in Duniyah(دُنِيَّا)
to eat food and you have your special dishes and the special flavors that you love.
It is one of the things that we as human beings enjoy.
If you think about it, if Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ, would make the digestive system transparent.
If Allah made the digestive system transparent, see through, digestive system,
so you can see what happens from the moment, the food goes in, until it gets out.
Imagine you're sitting with somebody in a restaurant, all right, and they eat that very juicy food.
And you see it mixing in the mouth, with the saliva, it's going up and down, till it becomes like a ball.
Then its swallowed.
And then it's not only see-through, but there's also pores for you to enjoy it with the five senses,
so you can see, you can hear, and you can smell.
And then you see it come out.
Do you think that people are going to eat together?
Do you think people will go to restaurants?
Do you  think that there's going to be even a business, called restaurant, in the world?
People are going to be so ashamed ,they're going to be eating in separate closets to hide away from the people.
So look at how the Shahawat(شهوات) of Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) that you love are so contaminated.
But in Akhirah(آخرة) none of that contamination exists.
People do not spit, they do not sweat, they do not urinate, they do not defecate, it is pure pleasure.
So there's a difference between Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) and Akhirah(آخرة).
Sorry for getting bit graphic.
Number 7). Attachment to a comfortable lifestyle.
It might be the tranquility of your mansion, the shade of your garden, the comfort of your bed,
the amenities of life that are surrounding you and making your life pleasant and pain free,
that is keeping you away from Jihad(جهاد) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله).
But remember that none of that would last forever.
Your mansion is nothing but stones bricks and mortar.
If it is not cleaned, it would rot and if it's not maintained, it would fall apart.
And eventually it would turn into the dirt it was made from.
Wouldn't you prefer to live in a palace built from bricks of gold and silver,
a palace that is everlasting and doesn't need cleaning or maintenance.
Its furniture is chosen and arranged by angels. Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ says:
وَنَمَارِقُ مَصْفُوفَةٌ
Numariq Masfoofah(وَنَمَارِقُ مَصْفُوفَةٌ) is the furniture, Masfoofah(مَصْفُوفَةٌ) laid out by who?
So the furniture of your mansion is laid out by the angels.
They are the ones, who choose where to put the furniture
and I think there's a special profession for that in Duniyah(دُنِيَّا). You know,
interior design, exactly interior design.
The interior designers of your mansions in Jannah(جنة) are angels
they will design the layout of your mansion in paradise.
So you would come with your wife and everything is just ready laid out for you.
It's furniture is chosen  and arranged by angels
in it, you will be served with the best food by servants whom Allah says about them:
وَيَطوفُ عَلَيهِم وِلدانٌ مُخَلَّدونَ إِذا رَأَيتَهُم حَسِبتَهُم لُؤلُؤًا مَنثورًا۞
They will circulate among them young boys made eternal,
when you see them, you would think them as beautiful as scattered pearls.
Al-Insaan(ألإنسان) Verse 19.
In Paradise, everything is clean. Everything is pure.
There's no call to nature or sweating. Our bodies will come in a different form.
ثُمَّ أَنشَأْنَاهُ خَلْقاً آخَرَ
Life then in is infinite. There's no time pressure.
The people of Paradise are free to do what they like whenever they like and for as long as they like.
One of them could recline on his throne for 40 years talking to his wife
only wonder what they would be talking about for 40 years.
Question From Audience:
That's in Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) in Akhirah(آخرة) you're gonna take revenge you're gonna be doing that.
Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله) when you think about this concept of time,
because there is no time limit in Akhirah(آخرة), because it's infinite, it's eternal.
If you come out of your mansion, for example, and you see a flower that you like,
you could sit there for 10 years watching it.
You know, you don't have any appointments, you don't have any work to do.
You could sit there for 100 years if you want.
There's no time pressure whatsoever.
So it's quite a difficult concept to think about
and when you carry it further,
you could even think about things like if you want to spend an entire year with Muhammadﷺ,
he would give you that time.
If you want, for example, you were reading in history and there were some things that you want to clarify
about Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) you could go and meet him and spend the entire month with him
to discuss what happened.
There's no time pressur, so there's no reason why this offer would be turned down.
If they're busy for the first billion years, you can meet them after that,
there is no time pressure whatsoever.
And that's why Ibn-Al-Qayyim(إبن لقيم) when he talks about in his book
about Jannah(جنة), he mentions some strange things. He says,
that a man would be sleeping with his wife for 80 years. I mean, do you think about 80 years!
Yani(يعني) he mentions that it's in a Hadith(حديث), but it might be a weak Hadith(حديث).
I think it's At-Tirmidhi(ألتِّرمِذِيْ).
But all these things are possible.
Because there's no time pressure whatsoever. You're free to do whatever you want.
You are given four rivers, you could go and spend the entire summer on this river enjoying its beauty.
Because there's No Limits
and our minds in Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) are not capable of thinking outside the box when it comes to time,
we cannot understand, you know, I understand what billion years means
what billion, billion years means but infinity, everlasting, never stops. It keeps on going.!
The Energizer Bunny would die, and you're still alive in Jannah(جنة).
Nothing stands between you and this enjoyment except dying as a Shaheed(شَهِيد).
Compare this lifestyle to what you have in this world.
Number 8). Desire to live longer to do more good deeds.
You might not want to participate in Jihad(جهاد) because you are not ready and you want to do more good deeds.
So you have a good intention in delaying Jihad(جهاد),
but let me tell you, that you are being deceived. Allah says:
يا أَيُّهَا النّاسُ إِنَّ وَعدَ اللَّهِ حَقٌّ ۖ
فَلا تَغُرَّنَّكُمُ الحَياةُ الدُّنيا ۖ وَلا يَغُرَّنَّكُم بِاللَّهِ الغَرورُ۞
إِنَّ الشَّيطانَ لَكُم عَدُوٌّ فَاتَّخِذوهُ عَدُوًّا ۚ
إِنَّما يَدعو حِزبَهُ لِيَكونوا مِن أَصحابِ السَّعيرِ۞
Oh mankind! Indeed, the promise of Allah is true.
So let not the worldly life delude you and Be not deceived about Allah by the deceiver.
Indeed, Satan is an enemy to you. So take him as an enemy.
He only invites his party to be among the companions of the blaze.
AL-Fatir(ألفاطر) Verse 5-6.
There is nothing more than a trap by Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ).
That is not the way of the Aouliya(أولياء) of Allah.
Weren’t the Sahabah(صحابه) and the Taba'een(تابعين) keener to do more good deeds than you?
But that never held them back from fighting in the cause of Allah.
Can't you hear Allah telling you:
انفِروا خِفافًا وَثِقالًا وَجاهِدوا بِأَموالِكُم
وَجاهِدوا بِأَموالِكُم وَأَنفُسِكُم في سَبيلِ اللَّهِ ۚ
ذٰلِكُم خَيرٌ لَكُم إِن كُنتُم تَعلَمونَ۞
Go forth whether light or heavy, and strive with your wealth and your lives in the cause of Allah?
That is better for you, If you only knew At-Tubah(ألتوبة) Verse 41.
Can't you see that the best way to better yourself is actually through Jihad(جهاد).
Allah says:
لا يَستَوِي القاعِدونَ مِنَ المُؤمِنينَ غَيرُ أُولِي الضَّرَرِ وَالمُجاهِدونَ في سَبيلِ اللَّهِ بِأَموالِهِم وَأَنفُسِهِم ۚ
فَضَّلَ اللَّهُ المُجاهِدينَ بِأَموالِهِم وَأَنفُسِهِم عَلَى القاعِدينَ دَرَجَةً ۚ
وَكُلًّا وَعَدَ اللَّهُ الحُسنىٰ ۚ
وَفَضَّلَ اللَّهُ المُجاهِدينَ عَلَى القاعِدينَ أَجرًا عَظيمًا۞
But Allah has preferred the Mujahideen(مجاهدين) over those who remain behind with a great reward.
Al-Nisa(ألنساء) Verse 95.
In fact there's nothing that compares to Jihad(جهاد),
the Messenger of Allah says: Standing in the ranks of the army in the battlefield
is greater than worshiping Allah among your family for 70 years.
That's in At-Tirmidhi(ألتِّرمِذِيْ), Bayhaqi(بيهقي) and Al-Hakim(ألحاكم).
Oh you, who have deceived yourself
realize that the sleep of the Mujahid(مُجَاهِد) is better than the praying of the night,
and the fasting of the day for everyone else.
Number 9). Love of your wife.
Tayeb(طيِّب), If you cannot go to Jihad(جهاد) because you are attached to a beautiful wife,
then even if you were to assume that your wife is the best woman in the whole world,
and that she is the most beautiful woman in the whole world.
Now didn't she start out as a lowly droplet and would end as a decomposed body.
And in between her birth and death, she never ceased carrying stool in her gut,
her menstrual period keeps you away from her for a good portion of her life,
her disobedience is more than her obedience.
If she does not wash, she would smell horrible.
If she doesn't comb, her hair becomes ruffled,
the older she gets the more ugly she becomes,
pleasing her is not easy.
And her love costs you a lot.
You're always trying to impress her. And nothing is ever enough.
She only loves you, when you give her what she wants.
And if you don't she would soon leave you and find someone else.
As if she's telling you, if you want me spend on me.
In general, you cannot enjoy her without enduring pain and suffering.
It is amazing how such a woman is keeping you away from the woman of paradise.
In the Name of Allah, the blood of the Shaheed(شَهِيد), does not dry before he meets his wife in paradise.
She is beautiful with big lustrous eyes, a virgin, as if she is an emerald.
She has loved no one, and will love, no one but you.
She was created for you and only you.
If her finger appears it would overshadow the moon.
If her bracelet appears in the dark night, it will leave no darkness in the universe.
If her wrist appears, it would take away the mind of every sane human being,
if she appears between the heaven and earth, the distance between them would be filled by her scent.
And if she splits in the oceans of the world, the salt water would turn fresh.
The more you look at her, the more beautiful, she becomes,
the more time you spend with her, the more you love her,
doesn't make any sense to learn about such a woman, and not try to meet her.
What about when you learn that you will not be married to one but 70 of the Hoor(حور).
Keep in mind that leaving your wife behind is inevitable.
You will die and so would she and In Sha Allah(إنْ شاءالله) you will be reunited in paradise.
And then you will find her to be even more beautiful than the Hoor(حور).
When that happens you will find her free of all of the contaminations of this worldly life,
wake up before it's too late.
Free yourself from the prison of this world, and pray to Allah to grant your martyrdom.
Don't let anything stand between you and this great reward.
Abu Hurairah(ابوهريره) narrates that the messenger of Allah said: The Shaheed(شَهِيد) feels the pain of death,
just like one of you would feel the sting of an insect.
And this Hadith(حديث) is Hasan(حسن),
it is narrated At-Tirmidhi(ألتِّرمِذِيْ), Nisai(نسائ), Ibn Majah(إبن ماجه) and Ahmad(أحمد).
So this is the end of Mo'adha(مؤعظه)
The of the virtues of Jihad(جهاد). Allah سبحانه تعالى says:
لا يَستَوِي القاعِدونَ مِنَ المُؤمِنينَ غَيرُ أُولِي الضَّرَرِ وَالمُجاهِدونَ في سَبيلِ اللَّهِ بِأَموالِهِم وَأَنفُسِهِم ۚ
فَضَّلَ اللَّهُ المُجاهِدينَ بِأَموالِهِم وَأَنفُسِهِم عَلَى القاعِدينَ دَرَجَةً ۚ
وَكُلًّا وَعَدَ اللَّهُ الحُسنىٰ ۚ
وَفَضَّلَ اللَّهُ المُجاهِدينَ عَلَى القاعِدينَ أَجرًا عَظيمًا۞
دَرَجاتٍ مِنهُ وَمَغفِرَةً وَرَحمَةً ۚ وَكانَ اللَّهُ غَفورًا رَحيمًا۞
Not equal are those believers remaining at home, Other than the disabled,
and the Mujahideen(مجاهدين) in the cause of Allah with their wealth and their lives.
Allah has preferred the Mujahideen(مجاهدين) through their wealth and their lives
over those who remain behind by degrees.
And to all, Allah has promised the best reward.
But Allah has preferred the Mujahideen(مجاهدين) over those who remained behind with a great reward,
degrees for him and forgiveness and mercy.
And Allah is Ever forgiving and merciful. An-Nisa(أنساء) Verse 95-96.
Now in this Ayah(آية) two things can be derived from it.
First of all, Jihad At-Talab(جهادألطلب) is Fardh Kifayah(فرض كفاية) and its not Fardh Ain(فرض عين).
That the offensive Jihad(جهاد) is Fardh Kifayah(فرض كفاية).
Because we mentioned that Saeed bin Musaib(سعيد بن مسيب) holds the view
that Jihad(جهاد) is Fardh Ain(فرض عين), we are talking about Jihad At-Talab(جهادألطلب).
But this Ayah(آية) is comparing between the two, and is saying that to all that Allah has promise reward.
So how can Allah say that is He is promising a reward, when somebody is doing a sin.
So this is an evidence that Jihad At-Talab(جهادألطلب), the offensive Jihad(جهاد) is Fardh Kifayah(فرض كفاية),
but it's also an evidence that Jihad(جهاد) is the best of deeds
that there there's nothing better than the Jihad(جهاد) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله),
because Allah explicitly states
that the Mujahideen(مجاهدين) are better than the Qaai’din(قاعدين)
and the Qaai’din(قاعدين) is talking about the Qaai’din(قاعدين) in general,
whether they are bad, whether they are scholars,
whether they are serving in the house of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
Whether they are giving Sadaqat(صدقات).
Al-Qaai’din(ألقاعدين) in general, no matter what they do, are lower in status than the Mujahid(مُجَاهِد) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله).
Allah says:
فَليُقاتِل في سَبيلِ اللَّهِ الَّذينَ يَشرونَ الحَياةَ الدُّنيا بِالآخِرَةِ ۚ
وَمَن يُقاتِل في سَبيلِ اللَّهِ فَيُقتَل أَو يَغلِب فَسَوفَ نُؤتيهِ أَجرًا عَظيمًا۞
So let those fight in the cause of Allah, who sells the life of this world for the hereafter.
And he who fight in the cause of a Allah and is killed or achieves victory.
We will bestow upon him a great reward,
An-Nisa(أنساء) Verse 74.
الَّذينَ آمَنوا وَهاجَروا وَجاهَدوا في سَبيلِ اللَّهِ بِأَموالِهِم
بِأَموالِهِم وَأَنفُسِهِم أَعظَمُ دَرَجَةً عِندَ اللَّهِ ۚ
وَأُولٰئِكَ هُمُ الفائِزونَ ۞
يُبَشِّرُهُم رَبُّهُم بِرَحمَةٍ مِنهُ وَرِضوانٍ وَجَنّاتٍ لَهُم فيها نَعيمٌ مُقيمٌ ۞
خالِدينَ فيها أَبَدًا ۚ
إِنَّ اللَّهَ عِندَهُ أَجرٌ عَظيمٌ۞
The ones, who have believed, emigrated and striven in the cause of Allah with their wealth and their lives,
are greater in rank in the sight of Allah.
And it is those who are the attainers, of success.
Their Lord gives them good tidings of mercy from Him
and approval, and of gardens for them wherein is enduring pleasure,
abiding therein forever indeed, Allah has with him a great reward,
At-Taubah(ألتوبة) Verse 20-22.
In At-Taubah(ألتوبة) Verse 111,
إِنَّ اللَّهَ اشتَرىٰ مِنَ المُؤمِنينَ أَنفُسَهُم وَأَموالَهُم
وَأَموالَهُم بِأَنَّ لَهُمُ الجَنَّةَ ۚ
يُقاتِلونَ في سَبيلِ اللَّهِ فَيَقتُلونَ وَيُقتَلونَ ۖ
وَعدًا عَلَيهِ حَقًّا فِي التَّوراةِ وَالإِنجيلِ وَالقُرآنِ ۚ
وَمَن أَوفىٰ بِعَهدِهِ مِنَ اللَّهِ ۚ
فَاستَبشِروا بِبَيعِكُمُ الَّذي بايَعتُم بِهِ ۚ
وَذٰلِكَ هُوَ الفَوزُ العَظيمُ۞
Indeed, Allah has purchased from the believers their lives and their properties
in exchange for that, they will have paradise.
They fight in the cause of Allah, so they kill and are killed.
It is a true promise binding upon him in the Torah(توراة) and the Gospel and the Qur'an,
and who is truer to his covenant than Allah.
So rejoice in your transaction, which you have contracted,
and it is that which is the great attainment.
Two things in this Ayah(آية). Number one,
إِنَّ اللَّهَ اشْتَرَىٰ
Allah has bought.
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ is offering you to buy your soul and your wealth,
Allah wants to buy something from you.
And that is your soul.
And Allah is offering you as one of the scholars said,
أشتارى منهم وأغلالهم سَمن
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ offered to buy from them, and he set a very, very high price.
Allah, is going to pay for the price of your soul, Jannah(جنة).
The most expensive commodity.
When the Ansaar(أنصار) were meeting with Rasool Allah ﷺ in ‘Baiyat-Ul-Aqabah As-Thaniya(بيعةالعقبة ألثانية),
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: This is what I want from you,
you testify that there's no God but Allah and that I’m the Messenger of Allah,
and you protect me from that which you protect your wives and children.
Therefore, this was called Bai'yah-Tun-Nisa(بيعةالنساء), the pledge of woman, Why?
Because Rasool Allah ﷺ is asking for the protection that the Ansaar(أنصار) would give to their woman and property.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said, this is what I want from you.
Abdullah Bin Rawaha(رواحة) said: That is what you're asking from us, what will we get in exchange.
I mean this is a deal here, we're negotiating a deal.
This is what you want from us, what are you going to pay us back.
Rasool Allah ﷺ did not tell them you're going to become wealthy.
He didn't say, I'm going to appoint you as ministers in my government.
He didn't tell them, you're going to become kings after I pass away.
Rasool Allah ﷺ told them,
لَكُم الجنة
You will get Jannah(جنة).!
What did the Ansaar(أنصار), says:
قَالُوا: رَبِحَ الْبَيْعُ لَا نُقِيلُ وَلَا نَسْتَقِيلُ
This is a very profitable deal. We will never back out of it.
So the agreement is that you give Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ your soul or your wealth, Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ in exchange will give you Jannah(جنة).
That's number one. Number two,
the Ayah(آية) says that this contract is even mentioned in the Torah(توراة) and Gospel.
You see with the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) of Allah, like Hud(هود), Saleh(صالح), Nooh(نوح)
it wasn’t part of their Shariah(شريعة) to fight, Qital(قتال) wasn’t part of their Shariah(شريعة),
Hood عليه السّلام and his followers were not given the instruction to fight.
They were given the instructions to leave,
and Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ through a supernatural event will destroy the enemy.
With Saleh عليه السّلام the same thing with Nooh عليه السّلام, the flood,
with Lut عليه السّلام, the destruction of the people of Lut(لوط),
so they were not given the command to fight.
This was a command reserved for the latter nations,
and the first Ummah(امة) to fight Jihad(جهاد) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله) is the Ummah(امة) of who?
Musa عليه السّلام
and that's what makes Bannu Israel(بنواسرائيل), the greatest Ummah(امة) after the Ummah(امة) of Muhammadﷺ
because it's an Ummah(امة) of Da'wah(دعوة) and Jihad(جهاد).
Therefore, this is something mentioned in the Tor'ah(توراة), and mentioned in an Injeel(إنجيل) and mentioned in Qur'an.
Muhammad(محمد) Verse 7.
يا أَيُّهَا الَّذينَ آمَنوا إِن تَنصُرُوا اللَّهَ يَنصُركُم وَيُثَبِّت أَقدامَكُم۞
Oh you have believed. If you support Allah, He will support you and plant firmly your feet.
In Al-Hujrat(ألحجرات) Verse15.
إِنَّمَا المُؤمِنونَ الَّذينَ آمَنوا بِاللَّهِ وَرَسولِهِ ثُمَّ لَم يَرتابوا
ثُمَّ لَم يَرتابوا وَجاهَدوا بِأَموالِهِم وَأَنفُسِهِم في سَبيلِ اللَّهِ ۚ
أُولٰئِكَ هُمُ الصّادِقونَ۞
The believers are only the ones, who have believed in Allah and His messenger
and then doubt not but strive make Jihad(جهاد) with their properties and their lives in the cause of Allah.
It is those who are truthful.
In As-Saff(ألصَّف), Verse 10 to 13.
يا أَيُّهَا الَّذينَ آمَنوا هَل أَدُلُّكُم عَلىٰ تِجارَةٍ تُنجيكُم مِن عَذابٍ أَليمٍ ۞
تُؤمِنونَ بِاللَّهِ وَرَسولِهِ وَتُجاهِدونَ في سَبيلِ اللَّهِ بِأَموالِكُم وَأَنفُسِكُم ۚ
ذٰلِكُم خَيرٌ لَكُم إِن كُنتُم تَعلَمونَ۞
يَغفِر لَكُم ذُنوبَكُم وَيُدخِلكُم جَنّاتٍ تَجري مِن تَحتِهَا الأَنهارُ
وَمَساكِنَ طَيِّبَةً في جَنّاتِ عَدنٍ ۚ
ذٰلِكَ الفَوزُ العَظيمُ ۞
وَأُخرىٰ تُحِبّونَها ۖ نَصرٌ مِنَ اللَّهِ وَفَتحٌ قَريبٌ ۗ
وَبَشِّرِ المُؤمِنينَ۞
Oh you have believed Shall I guide you to a transaction that will save you from painful punishment.
It is that you believe in Allah and His messenger
and strive in the cause of Allah with your wealth and your lives, that is best for you.
If you should, but know.
He will forgive you your sins and admit you to gardens beneath which rivers flow,
and pleasant dwellings in gardens of perpetual residence.
That is a great attainment.
And you will obtain another favor that you love, victory from Allah, and an eminent conquest
and give good tidings to the believers.
Jihad(جهاد) is the best deed after Salah(صلاة) and being dutiful towards one's parents,
the Messenger of Allah was asked:
What is the most beloved act of worship in the eyes of Allah.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Praying on time.
I said: Then what?
He said: Being dutiful towards your parents.
I said: Then what? He said: Jihad(جهاد) in the path of Allah.
This Hadith(حديث) is in Bukhari(بخاريْ).
Ibn-e-Umar(إبن عمر) used to consider Jihad(جهاد) to be the best of all deeds after Salah(صلاة).
And this is mentioned by Al-Bahaqi(ألبيهقي).
The next heading: Jihad(جهاد) is the greatest deed, after believing in Allah.
Rasool Allah ﷺ was asked, what is the best of all acts of worship.
He said: Believing in Allah.
He was then asked, and then what?
He responded: Jihad(جهاد) in the path of Allah.
Then he was asked, and then what?
He said an accepted Hajj(حَجْ).
That's in Bukhari(بخاريْ) and Muslim(مسلم).
In Musnad Imam Ahmad(مَسنداِمَامْ اَحْمَدْ), Ma'az(معز) narrates the Messenger of Allah was asked, what is the best deed.?
He said: Believing in Allah, and then Jihad(جهاد), and then Hajj(حَجْ), which would be, better than every other deed,
like the distance between the sunset, and the sunrise.
So, believing in Allah, Jihad(جهاد) and Hajj(حَجْ) are way above everything else.
These three deeds are above everything else, this is between sunrise and sunset.
In Bukhari(بخاريْ) and Muslim(مسلم) Abu Dhar(ابوذر) narrates, I asked the Messenger of Allah above the best deeds.
He said believing in Allah and Jihad(جهاد) in His path.
Abu Qatadah(أبوقتادة) narrates that the Messenger of Allah stood and delivered a reminder to them
and said that Jihad(جهاد) in the path of Allah, and believing in Allah are the greatest deeds.
A man stood up and asked, Oh messenger of Allah:
What if I was killed in the path of Allah would my sins be forgiven,
the Messenger of Allah said: Yes!
And this is in Muslim(مسلم).
Abu Hurairah(ابوهريره) narrates that the Messenger of Allah said:
The best of deeds in  eyes of Allah are, a belief in Allah with conviction,
the Ghazoo(غزؤ) with no Ghalool(غلول).
Ghalool(غلول) is money unlawfully taken from the Ghanimah(غنيمه),
and an acceptable Hajj(حَجْ).
The next heading:
Jihad(جهاد) is greater than worshiping in the house of Allah and serving it and serving the pilgrims.
An-Noman Ibn Bashir(نعمان إبن بشير) narrates. I was sitting next to the pulpit of the Messenger of Allah.
When a man came and said:
I wouldn't mind if I don't do anything after becoming a Muslim but serving the pilgrims,
meaning after saying:
أَشْهَدُ أَنْ لَا إِلَهَ إِلَّا اللَّهُ وَأَشْهَدُ أَنَّ مُحَمَّدًا رَسُول الله
I wouldn't mind doing nothing but serving the pilgrims, meaning I consider this to be the best of deeds.
Another man said: I wouldn't mind if I don't do anything after becoming a Muslim but praying in the sacred Masjid(مسجد),
in Masjid-Al-Haram(ألمسجدالحرام).
A third man said: No! Jihad(جهاد) in the path of Allah is better than what you said.
So Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) scolded them
and told them to stay quiet and not raise their voices next to the pulpit of the Messenger of Allah.
He then said, this is Friday, and in short while, Muhammadﷺ will come out of his house and give us Khut'ba(خطبة).
And I'll ask him about what you said.
He asked Muhammadﷺ and Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ revealed the Ayah(آية).
أَجَعَلتُم سِقايَةَ الحاجِّ وَعِمارَةَ المَسجِدِ الحَرامِ كَمَن
كَمَن آمَنَ بِاللَّهِ وَاليَومِ الآخِرِ وَجاهَدَ في سَبيلِ اللَّهِ ۚ
لا يَستَوونَ عِندَ اللَّهِ ۗ
وَاللَّهُ لا يَهدِي القَومَ الظّالِمينَ۞
Have you made the providing of water for the pilgrim,
and the maintenance of the Masjid-Al-Haram(ألمسجدالحرام),
equal to one, who believes in Allah and the Last Day and mixed Jihad(جهاد) in His cause.
They are not equal in the sight of Allah
and Allah does not guide the wrong doing people.
And this Hadith(حديث) is in Muslim(ألمسلم).
So this Ayah(آية), explicitly states that Jihad(جهاد) is better than serving the pilgrims in Masjid-Al-Haram(ألمسجدالحرام)
and worshipping Allah in Masjid-Al-Haram(ألمسجدالحرام).
Tayeb(طيِّب), References that Jihad(جهاد) is the greatest deed of all.
Amr Bin Absa(عمروبن عبسة) narrates, a man came to the Messenger of Allah and said: What is Islam.?
He said: Islam is submission of your heart, and that the Muslims are safe from your tongue and your hands.
He said: What is the best of Islam?
The Messenger of Allah said: Eeman(ايمان)!
He said: And what is Eeman(ايمان)?
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: To believe in Allah, His angels, His books, His messengers and the resurrection after death.
He said: What is the best of Eeman(ايمان)?
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Hijrah(هجرة)!
He said: What is Hijrah(هجرة)?
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: To leave sins behind.
He said: What is the best of Hijrah(هجرة)?
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Jihad(جهاد)!
He then said: What is the best of Jihad(جهاد)?
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: The one, whose horse is slain, and His blood is spilled.
And this is in Ahmad(أحمد), Tabrani(طبراني) and Bahaqi(بيهقي).
So now again. He asked about Islam.
He then asked what is the best of Islam? Rasool Ullah told him. Eeman(ايمان)!
He said: Then, what is the best of the Eeman(ايمان).?
He said: The best of Eeman(ايمان) is Hijrah(هجرة).
What's the best of the Hijrah(هجرة)?
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Jihad(جهاد)!
And what's the best of Jihad(جهاد)? Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Martyrdom!
Therefore, Jihad(جهاد) becomes the best, of the best, of the best.
And then the best of that is martyrdom.
So it's the cream of the cream of the cream.
The Messenger of Allah told the man become a Muslim.
The man said: What is Islam?
He responded to him and then he asked him about Hijrah(هجرة) and Jihad(جهاد),
the man said: What is Jihad(جهاد).?
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: You fight in the cause of Allah
and you do not fear fighting the enemy,
and you do not commit Ghalool(غلول),
and that is in Bayhaqi(البيهقي).
In Bukhari(بخاريْ), Ayesha(عائشه) narrates that she told the Messenger of Allah,
O messenger of Allah, we see that Jihad(جهاد) in the Cause of Allah is the Greatest deed.
Shouldn't we then make Jihad(جهاد).
So, here the Hadith(حديث) is saying that the even the women used to considered Jihad(جهاد) to be the greatest of deeds.
I mean, it was common knowledge, that is the greatest of deeds.
Rasool Allah ﷺ told them for you the best Jihad(جهاد) is Hajj Mabror(حج مبرور).
Abu Hurairah(ابوهريره) narrates that the Messenger of Allah said:
The Jihad(جهاد) of the old, the weak and the women is Hajj(حَجْ) and Umrah(عمرة).
Al-Khateeb Al-Bagdadi(ألخطيب ألبغدادي) mentions in the history of Baghdad,
and Ibn Asakir(إبن عساكر) mentions in the history of Damascus
that Muhammad Ibn Fudhail Ibn Ayyadh(محمدإبن فضيل إبن عياض), said:
I saw Ibn Al-Mubarak(إبن ألمبارك) in my dream.
Ibn Al-Mubarak(إبن ألمبارك) and Fudhail Bin Ayyadh(فضيل بن عياض) were friends.
But they we're following two different tracks.
Ibn Al-Mubarak(إبن ألمبارك) was a scholar of Jihad(جهاد)
and Al-Fuzail(ألفضيل) was a scholar of Ibadah(عبادة).
So both of them were scholars, but one of them chose the track of Jihad(جهاد),
and the other one chose the track of a Ibadah(عبادة).
And there's the famous lines of poetry.
When Ibn Al-Mubarak(إبن ألمبارك) sends a letter to his friend Fudhail Bin Ayyadh(فضيل بن عياض), and he tells him,
يا عبدالحرمين يا أبصرتنا۞۞۞  ألعلمتا اَنَّك باالعبادة فالعبد۞۞۞
O, the one, who was worshipping next to Al-Haram(ألحرم),
if you see us, you would realize that your worship is nothing but playing, compared to what we are doing.
So he saw Ibn Al-Mubarak(إبن ألمبارك) in a dream.
Ibn Al-Mubarak(إبن ألمبارك) passed away before him.
He saw him in a dream.
So I asked him: What did you, find your best deeds to be?
He said: The deed that I preoccupied myself with, the deed that kept me busy.
I asked: Jihad(جهاد) and Ribat(رباط).?
He said: Yes!
I told him. What did Allah do to you.? He said: He forgave me, he forgave me.
And it's common to see dreams of Salaheen(ألصالحين) and the Shuhadaa(شُهَدآء),
and to ask him what happened to you?
This is a dream that happens quite frequently.
Al-Fadhal Bin Zaid(الفضل بن زيد) said: I heard about Abu Abdullah Imam Ahmed(أبوعبدالله إمام أحمد),
when Ghazoo(غزؤ) was mentioned to him.
So Imam Ahmad Bin Hanbal(إمام أحمد بن حنبل) was sitting in a Halaqah(حلقه) and
the issue of Jihad(جهاد) was brought up so Imam Ahmad(اِمَامْ اَحْمَدْ) started to cry.
And then he said: There is no act of worship greater than it,
there is nothing greater than Jihad(جهاد) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله).
In Al-Mughni(ألمغني) it states that Imam Ahmad(اِمَامْ اَحْمَدْ) said:
There is nothing comparable in rewards to meeting the enemy.
And for one to involve in the actual fighting is the best of deeds.
And this is compared to supportive roles.
So again, there's nothing comparable in rewards to meeting the enemy.
And for one to involve in the actual fighting is the best of deeds,
the ones who are fighting the enemy, are the ones defending Islam.
So what can be greater than that.
People feel safe, while they feel fear, they have given up their souls for Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
These are the words of Imam Ahmad رضي الله عنه.
Jihad(جهاد) is the most beloved deed to Allah.
Now when we were talking about the best deed, you find the some Ahadith(احاديث), It says Jihad(جهاد).
In some Ahadith(احاديث), it says: Being dutiful towards your parents.
There's some Ahadith(احاديث) it that says: Zikr(زكر) of Allah,
another Hadith(حديث), it would says: Eeman(ايمان) in Allah.
How do you reconcile between this?
I mean, the best thing should be the best deed.
Yani(يعني) you can't have more than one thing that all of them are the best.
How do you reconcile.?
Tayeb(طيِّب) that's one way to reconcile, for example,
when one man came to Rasool Ullah, and this was a tough man married to nine women.
Rasool Allah ﷺ told him first of all you have to divorce five,
and then you got to Jihad(جهاد) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله).
Another man came to Rasool Allah ﷺ, he was old in age,
He told him: O Rasool Ullah tell me what to do? Rasool Ullah told him: Make zikr(زكر).
So, the context of these two people, is clear that Rasool Allah ﷺ was giving them an answer according to their ability.
Is there another way to reconcile.?
What about it.?
So the Ayah(آية) makes it clear that Jihad(جهاد) is the best.
Tayeb(طيِّب) there is an argument placed by one of the scholars that because of this Ayah(آية),
and also the first Ayah(آية) that we read that the Mujahid(مُجَاهِد) is better than the Qaid(قائد)
that there is a deed, that is, that is the best in general.
But then there are other deeds that are better in specific situations.
So there's one deed, that is the best.
And then there are other deeds that are in exceptional situations, the best.
And the argument is based on the fact that the Ayah(آية), the Ayah(آية) of a As-Saff(ألصف),
and the Ayah(آية) of An-Nisa(ألنساء) state that the Mujahid(مُجَاهِد) is better than the Qaaid(قائد).
So, this gives a general rule, this establishes a general rule.
The  exceptions to that rule are situations where a person is not able to do Jihad(جهاد).
So, then, in other specific situations, so you'd have something like being dutiful towards the parents, or making a Zikr(زكر) or Hajj(حَجْ).
Like for example with a women.
And this opinion would make more sense because the Ayaat(آيات) of Quran do set the rule,
and Ayaat(آيات) of Qur'an make it clear that in general Jihad(جهاد) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله) is the best of all deeds.
Abdullah Bin Salam(عبدالله بن سلام), said:
We were a group of the companions and Abdullah Bin Salam(عبدالله بن سلام) is the Jewish Rabbi, who became Muslim,
Abdullah Bin Salam(عبدالله بن سلام).
And Rasool Allah ﷺ gave him Shahadah(شَهَادَة) of Jannah(جنة), he is in Jannah(جنة).
He says we were a group of the companions of the Messenger of Allah, and we said:
If we just knew what was the most beloved deed to Allah.
Allah then revealed:
سَبَّحَ لِلَّهِ ما فِي السَّماواتِ وَما فِي الأَرضِ ۖ وَهُوَ العَزيزُ الحَكيمُ ۞
يا أَيُّهَا الَّذينَ آمَنوا لِمَ تَقولونَ ما لا تَفعَلونَ ۞
كَبُرَ مَقتًا عِندَ اللَّهِ أَن تَقولوا ما لا تَفعَلونَ ۞
إِنَّ اللَّهَ يُحِبُّ الَّذينَ يُقاتِلونَ في سَبيلِهِ صَفًّا
صَفًّا كَأَنَّهُم بُنيانٌ مَرصوصٌ۞
Whatever is in the heavens and whatever is on earth exalts Allah
and He is the Exalted in Might, and Wise.
Oh you, who have believed: Why do you say, what you do not do.
Great is hatred in the sight of Allah that you say, but you do not do.
Indeed, Allah loves those, who fight in his cause in a row,
as though they are a single structure joined firmly.
So Allah is saying that the deed that He loves most is that you fight in rank joined firmly.
And the Hadith(حديث) itself in At-Tirmidhi(ألتِّرمِذِيْ), Bayhaqi(بيهقي), Al-Hakim(ألحاكم) and Ibn-e-Mubarak(إبن مبارك).
The Mujahid(مُجَاهِد) is the greatest of all people, Allah says:
لا يَستَوِي القاعِدونَ مِنَ المُؤمِنينَ غَيرُ أُولِي الضَّرَرِ وَالمُجاهِدونَ في سَبيلِ اللَّهِ بِأَموالِهِم وَأَنفُسِهِم ۚ
فَضَّلَ اللَّهُ المُجاهِدينَ بِأَموالِهِم وَأَنفُسِهِم عَلَى القاعِدينَ دَرَجَةً ۚ
وَكُلًّا وَعَدَ اللَّهُ الحُسنىٰ ۚ
وَفَضَّلَ اللَّهُ المُجاهِدينَ عَلَى القاعِدينَ أَجرًا عَظيمًا۞
دَرَجاتٍ مِنهُ وَمَغفِرَةً وَرَحمَةً ۚ
وَكانَ اللَّهُ غَفورًا رَحيمًا۞
Allah has preferred the Mujahideen(مجاهدين) over those, who remain behind, with the great reward.
Degrees from Him and forgiveness and mercy.
And Allah is Ever forgiving and Merciful.
An-Nisa(ألنِّساء) Verse 95 and 96.
Rasool Allah ﷺ was asked in this Hadith(حديث) in Bukhari(بخاريْ) and Muslim(ألمسلم),
who is the best of people?
He said: A believer who is making Jihad(جهاد) with his life and his wealth, in the cause of Allah.
The next heading:
No one can practice any act of worship, equivalent to Jihad(جهاد).
In Sahih Muslim(صحيح ألمسلم)
Abu Hurairah(ابوهريره) narrates that the Messenger of Allah was asked about a deed equal in reward to Jihad(جهاد),
he replied, You cannot do it.
They asked again.
And then a third time, and every time the Messenger of Allah would say you cannot do it.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ said: The equivalent of the Mujahid(مُجَاهِد), is the one who fasts
and prays continuously without resting until the Mujahid(مُجَاهِد) comes back.
And we did talk about this Hadith(حديث) yesterday,
so I'll skip the others that are similar to it.
Abu Hurairah(ابوهريره) says, this is a statement by Abu Hurairah(ابوهريره),
he says: The horse of the Mujahid(مُجَاهِد), would be running in a pasture land,
and the Mujahid(مُجَاهِد) would be given rewards for that.
His horse is just roaming around, and the Mujahid(مُجَاهِد) would be rewarded for that.
Ibn Nuhas(إبن نُحاس) says: If the ones, with high aspirations,
those who had their rewards multiplied because of their companionship of the Messenger of Allah.
If they cannot find anything equivalent to Jihad(جهاد), then how can we be at ease with lower deeds.?
How can we settle for other deeds, when even then, we might have the mixed with insincerity and shortcomings.
Oh Allah wake us up from this sleep and grant us Jihad(جهاد) in your cause before it's too late.
You are our hope for any good, and there is no strength with anyone but You.
He is saying that the Sahabah(صحابه), who are with Rasool Allah ﷺ, they never gave up Jihad(جهاد),
even though they were the highest status of being companions of Rasool Allah ﷺ, living with him.
So what are we to do.?
The next heading:
References that the sleep of the Mujahid(مُجَاهِد) is better than the praying of the night, and fasting of the day, for others.
Safwan Bin Saleem(صفوان بن سليم) said: Abu Hurairah(ابوهريره) asked:
Can any one of you pray continuously without rest, and fast continuously without a break,
they said: O Abu Hurairah(ابوهريره), who could do that.
He said: I swear in the name of Allah, the sleep of the Mujahid(مُجَاهِد) is better than that.
So other people would be praying the whole night fasting the day struggling in Ibadah(عبادة)
and the Mujahid(مُجَاهِد) is asleep, and it's still making more Ajr(أجْر).
What about if the Mujahid(مُجَاهِد) would spend the night, in worshipping Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ and fasting the day?
Ibn Nuhas(إبن نُحاس), he actually says: If this is the status of their sleep.
Then what about their prayers.
This is what the competitors should compete for, and this is what others should cry for missing.
The next heading:
Allah reserved 100 levels in paradise for the Mujahideen(مجاهدين)
between each level and the other is the distance between the heavens and earth.
Abu Hurairah(ابوهريره) states that the Messenger of Allah said:
There are 100 levels in paradise, especially prepared by Allah for the Mujahideen(مجاهدين).
In His cause between each level and the next is the difference between the heaven and earth.
So when you ask Allah asked him to grant you, Al-firdous(ألفردوس),
it is in the middle of Paradise and the highest part of it,
from it, the rivers of paradise spring and above it is the Throne of Allah.
This is in Bukhari(بخاريْ).
Are you fine, we carry on, you're not getting tired.?
The next heading:
The Rahbania(رهبانية) and Siyaha(سياحة) of this Ummah(امة) is Jihad(جهاد).
What is the Rahbania(رهبانية)? And what is Siyaha(سياحة)?
Rahbania(رهبانية) is monetarism,
some Christian Orders, used to practice Rahbania(رهبانية).
Rahbania(رهبانية) is when they, we would say, Divorce this world, so they will not get married.
And they would not enjoy food and drink, and they will stay away from all of the fittan(فتن) of Duniyah(دُنِيَّا).
And they would lock themselves up in monasteries,
in caves, in mountain peaks, devoting their time to worshiping Allah.
So it's a very tough lifestyle and they're doing it for the sake of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
Now Allah says in Qur'an that this was something that wasn't prescribed on them.
They did it, but Allah did not ordered them to do it.
But it was very prevalent among specially Eastern Christians,
you know among Western Christians, they are not into this.
There is more materialism, in the West, for them to follow that truth and that's why you would find in the Hadith(حديث).
It says the Romans, it doesn't say the Christians, even though they are Christian,
because Christianity for the West is more of an identity and association,
than it is something that is practiced,
Just like when Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) was told about this Christian Arab tribe of Tae(طئ),
Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) said: They know nothing about Christianity except drinking wine.
They're not religious people, that's all they know about Christianity.
So, this Ta'abud(تعبد), monotheism existed among the Eastern Christians like for example in Abyssinia,
Egypt, Syria, Turkey.
There were many of these Rahban(رهبان), who devoted themselves to worshiping, and Ibadah(عبادة).
And it is something that some of Sahabah(صحابه) looked up to in the beginning of the Da'wah(دعوة),
it is said that some of the Sahabah(صحابه), were thinking about leading a life of Rahbania(رهبانية),
but then Rasool Allah ﷺ, prohibited them from doing that.
And then we also have the Hadith(حديث) of the three men who came to ask the wives of Rasool Allah ﷺ about his life at home.
So, one of them said: I don't marry woman, the other one said: I don't sleep and the other one said: I never break my fast.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: But I fast, some days and don't fast others.
And I pray part of the night and I sleep.
And I marry women, and that is my Sunnah(سنة).
And whoever is different than my Sunnah(سنة), doesn't belong to me.
Then there is Siyaha(سياحة),
Siyaha(سياحة) is similar to Rahbania(رهبانية), but they would travel.
So these were people who didn't have a fixed base,
they didn't have a home, they don't have families,
they just traveled in the earth contemplating the creation of Allah.
Now the word Siyaha(سياحة) in Arabic mean travelling.
And now, tourism is called Siyaha(سياحة).
Rasool Allah ﷺ says: That the Rahbania(رهبانية) and Siyaha(سياحة) of this Ummah(امة) is Jihad(جهاد) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله).
In other words Rahbania(رهبانية) is replaced
and Siyaha(سياحة) is replaced with Jihad(جهاد) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله).
So we're not allowed to do Rahbania(رهبانية) and Siyaha(سياحة) anymore but we should do Jihad(جهاد) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله).
A man came to the Messenger of Allah and said: Advise me!
He said: Have Taqwa(تقوى) of Allah, since it is the essence of our good
and make Jihad(جهاد), since it is the monotheism of this nation.
And remember Allah and recite Qur'an since it is light for you in this world,
and remembrance for you in the heavens and preserve your tongue except from Good.
For you would then defeat Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ).
Abu Abdullah Al-Halimi(ابوعبدالله ألحليمي), he says:
The meaning of the monotheism of this nation is Jihad(جهاد).
Is that the Christians used to practice monotheism by leading a secluded life in a monastery,
the maximum sacrifice they would give to Allah, is to stay away from the allurements of this world,
they would claim that they are staying away from everyone,
in order not to harm anyone,
but there is no harm, greater than leaving the evildoers practice their evil.
Therefore, the real ones, who are avoiding evil and harm, are the Mujahideen(مجاهدين) who are stamping evil out.
So, Rahban(رهبان), they stayed in the monastery so that they can stay away from evil.
But with this Ummah(امة), you stay away from evil by destroying it.
So that's the difference between this Ummah(امة) and the Ummam(امم) before.
Because see evil will never leave you alone.
It will keep on encroaching on your territory, until it eliminates you.
This world since the time of Adam(آدم), the history is about the conflict of Haqq(حَقّ) and Batil(باطل), good and evil.
And even if you leave evil alone, it will not leave you alone.
Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ), will never leave you alone.
He will always try to get you, therefore the only way is not to run away from Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ),
and show him your back, but to face Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ) and fight him.
And Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله), the majority are tourists.
They get to see the beauty of the creation of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
They get to live close to the creation of Allah, you see this, this urban lifestyle.
It leaves scars on the on the heart.
When you're living in a concrete jungle and, all what your living under is, artificial life and everything around you is artificial,
it affects your spirit because as a human being, you're created from this earth you created from the Turab(تراب) of this earth.
And when you're far away from nature, somehow it affects you.
But the Mujahid(مُجَاهِد), he is close to nature
he enjoys nature, He make Tafakur(تفكر) in the Khalq(خلق) of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
He gets to see the stars, he gets to see the beauty in the Khalq(خلق) of Allah, and mountains, valleys, rivers,
he eats from the different Rizq(رزق), different food from all over the world,
so really he is as Siyah-As-Sabeel(سياحة السبيل),
Siyaha(سياحة) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله عزوجل).
And in the same time it is Rahbania(رهبانية),
Ibadah(عبادة), reciting Qur'an, Zikr(زكر) of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ, Salah(صلاة), fasting, Talab-Ul-Ilm(طلب ألعلم).
Sahabah رضي الله عنهم who are living in Arabia,
they traveled all over the world. Spreading the religion of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
On the tape that talks about the life of Khattab(خطاب).
There's one segment where is walking in this beautiful scenery, in Chechnya,
and he is just looking around at these mountains and trees.
And then he sits on a broken log and he says,
سَيَاحة أمَّتي الجهاد في سبيل الله
Tourism of my Ummah(امة) is Jihad(جهاد) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله).
He is enjoying of Khalq(خلق) of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
The pinnacle of Islam is Jihad(جهاد).
Actually, let me read you the statement of the Hadith(حديث) of Siyaha(سياحة) in Abu Umamah(أبوأمامة)
narrates the Messenger of Allah said: The Siyaha(سياحة) of my nation is Jihad(جهاد).
This is an Abu Daud(أبوداؤد) and Al-Hakim(ألحاكم).
And then, Ibn Nuhas(إبن نُحاس) says: Siyaha(سياحة) is the traveling in the earth to flee evil,
and to contemplate in the creation of Allah.
Since Jihad(جهاد) involves all of that, it becomes the Siyaha(سياحة),
because the Mujahid(مُجَاهِد) is fleeing towards the Creator.
The pinnacle of Islam is Jihad(جهاد).
Muadh ibn Jabal( معاذ إبن جبل) narrates:
We were with the Messenger of Allah returning from Tabook(تبوك), he told me:
If you want I can tell you, the head of the matter, its pillar and its peak,
I said: Yes! O messenger of Allah,
he said: The head of the matter is Islam.
Its pillar is Salah(صلاة) and its peak as Jihad(جهاد).
This is in Al-Hakim(ألحاكم), Ahmad(أحمد), At-Tirmidhi(ألتِّرمِذِيْ), and Ibn-e-Majah(إبن ماجه).
The Mujahid(مُجَاهِد) is given a guaranteed by Allah.
In Bukhari(بخاريْ) and Muslim(ألمسلم), Abu Hurairah(ابوهريره) narrates,
the Messenger of Allah said: Allah has guaranteed the Mujahid(مُجَاهِد), who leaves from his home
with no purpose, but to fight in the Cause of Allah, and believe in your last words,
Allah has guaranteed for him, either to enter him into paradise,
or to return him home with a reward or booty.
So you're going out with a guarantee. If you die you go to Jannah(جنة),
if not, you're going to come back with Ajr(أجْر) and Ghanimah(غنيمه).
Abu Hurairah(ابوهريره) narrates the Messenger of Allah said:
There are three, whom it is granted that Allah will help them.
The Mujahid(مُجَاهِد) in the path of Allah, the slave who started the process of Mukatiba(مكاتبه) to free himself.
And the one, who wants to marry for chastity.
This is in Abdur Razzaq(عبدالرزاق), At-Tirmidhi(ألتِّرمِذِيْ) and Al-Hakim(ألحاكم).
The next heading:
is, Allah will never forsake the Mujahideen(مجاهدين), but would help them and respond to their prayers.
Jabir Bin Abdullah(جابرإبن عبدالله) narrates we were sent on an expedition by the Messenger of Allah,
to raid a caravan, owned by Quraish(قُرَيْشْ),
and he appointed Abu Hurairah(ابوهريره), as our leader.
This is an interesting story and it's in Sahih Muslim(صحيح ألمسلم).
Jabir Bin Abdullah(جابرإبن عبدالله) is narrating the story. He was a member of this Sariyah(سرية).
You have Ghazwa(غزوة) and Sariyah(سرية), Ghazwa(غزوة) is a battle in which Rasool Allah ﷺ participated in.
And then you have Sariyah(سرية), which is an army that Rasool Allah ﷺ did not join or it's a smaller army.
This was part of the economical war that Rasool Allah ﷺ was waging against Quraish(قُرَيْشْ),
it is to stifle Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), economically,
it's sort of an embargo on Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) to threaten their financial interests,
he would strike at their caravans.
So he sent Abu Hurairah(ابوهريره) to a place called Saif-Al-Bahr(سيف ألبحر).
So they went out and the Muslims were quite poor at that time.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ had nothing to give them, but leather bags filled with dates.
That's all.!
Abu Obaidah(أبوعبيدة) would hand us one date per day.
So the narrator, the one who is hearing from Jabir Bin Abdullah(جابرإبن عبدالله),
he is asking him and what would one date, do.?
How could you survive on one date a day.?
So Jabir(جابر) said: We would eat it and then suck on the date seed.
And then we would just drink water.
So they will eat the date and just keep on sucking on that seed.
Try to get whatever nutrition they can and they will drink water that's it.
And they were starving. Going for days.
Living on nothing but water, and one date per day.
And while they were traveling on the coast.
They saw what appeared to be a sand dune.
But when they got closer, they found that it's not the sand dune but it's a whale,
that was stranded on the beach, it was dead.
So they said, this is Maytah(مَيتَة) we cannot eat it.
Now, when they say it's Maytah(مَيتَة).
Either this was before the Maytah(مَيتَة) of the sea was allowed dead fish,
or it was because it might have been there for some time, so it wasn't fresh.
So Abu Obaidah(أبوعبيدة) said: Don't eat from it.
But then after that, they're very hungry.
So Abu Hurairah(ابوهريره) said:
We are the messengers of the Messenger of Allah and we are Mujahideen(مجاهدين) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله).
So go ahead and eat from it.
So they would go and eat from this fish.
The narrator of the Hadith(حديث) says that, Abu Hurairah(ابوهريره) wanted to see, how big the fish was.
So we had 13 of us, sit inside the eye socket of the whale,
the eye socket was enough for 13.
He said he took a rib bone and he placed it on the ground.
And then he had the tallest camel, and the taller Soldier ride on that camel.
And then he would go under the rib bone without knocking his head, it was huge.
The narrator of the Hadith(حديث) says:
We would pick up buckets of oil from the eye socket,
it's not oil but they would call it oil, it's fluid that you have in eye and they would eat it.
He said: We would carve out pieces of flesh as big as a bull.
He said: We would bring wood and put it under the just on the side,
and keep it burning, and then go and grab from the meat and eat from it.
He said: We stayed there for 30 days eating from that fish.
Until we ended up gaining weight.
He said: The flesh of our stomach was folding.
Imagine for 30 days eating from this fish eating nothing but seafood,
and how large was this Sariyah(سرية).?
They were 300.
Three hundred were eating day and night, fish.
And then when they were leaving, they had some of that meat and they would dry it,
they would dry it in the sun, and they carried with them some back to Madina.
When they arrived to Madina, they told Rasool Allah ﷺ about the story,
to ask him whether what they have done was right or wrong,
Rasool Allah ﷺ said:
ذالك رزق
That is Rizq(رزق), that was sent to you by Allah, did you bring me some.?
So they said: Yes! We did and they gave Rasool Allah ﷺ some of it and he wanted to eat it.
And this is an indication that the Rizq(رزق) that Allah gives to Mujahideen(مجاهدين) is Mubarak(مبارك), it's blessed,
because Rasool Allah ﷺ in Madina, wanted to eat some of it,
and they gave him some of that because Rasool Ullah said that, that was Rizq(رزق) that was sent to you by Allah,
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ sent that whale to the Red Sea to be stranded on the beach, as a gift to these Mujahideen(مجاهدين).
So the Mujahid(مُجَاهِد) shouldn't worry about the Rizq(رزق),
the Mujahid(مُجَاهِد) starts out his day and he doesn't know where he's gonna eat from,
but the Rizq(رزق) of Allah comes to the Mujahid(مُجَاهِد),
and Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله) it has the best taste and flavor, no matter what it is.
Because it's Rizq(رزق) that comes from Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ to the Mujahid(مُجَاهِد),
they might be eating things that you could never imagine that you would eat in the comfort of your home.
And nevertheless, it would taste best and the best restaurant that you have.
It's a gift from Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
Also something else that I could maybe add here is that,
you know, nutritionist now tell us that you're not supposed to eat meat and live on vegetables and fruits.
I mean, the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم for thirty days were eating nothing but fish.
The Rizq(رزق), that Allah سبحانه تعالى has made Halal(حلال), you eat from it, whatever you can.
And Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ would put Barakah(بركة), in the food that you eat.
One should not refrain from Halal(حلال) food because of what the nutritionist say.
You know, red meat is not good for you and all that stuff, who said that?
Yani(يعني) red meat is not good for you?
It's Halal(حلال) not only that but even fat is good for you, because if it wasn't good.
If it wasn't good, Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ would not make it Haram(حرام) on Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) as a punishment for them.
The thing is here, not to have the Israaf(إسراف).
Israaf(إسراف) in everything is not good, even Israaf(إسراف) in fruits or vegetables.
The Muslim is not supposed to have the Israaf(إسراف),
again they issue of fat now, if you tell a nutritionist that you're eating fat.
And the Ayah(آية) says in Qur'an that we made it Haram(حرام) and Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) as a punishment for them.
Therefore, fat is the Tayibaat(طيبات).
It's from a Tayibaat(طيبات).
You know there's two types of lamb.
Two species, one has a straight tail.
The other one has a big blubber of fat in the back, you know that type, it has a big blubber of fat.
In Afghanistan what the Mujahideen(مجاهدين) would do, they would take that big blubber of fat and they would dry it,
and they would cut it into cubes.
And they would dry those cubes.
And then when they run out of food,
or even if they have food, the snacks for the Mujahideen(مجاهدين) was, they would take the leftover of the bread.
You know dry bread that was left over.
And they would heat, those cubes of fat which have been stored, only Allah knows how long?
They might even have a smell.
They would heat that fat so it would turn into oil,
and then they would fry the leftovers in that oil, and they would eat it,
it's like potato chips or nachos, it's was pure fat.
It's pure fat, tell a nutritionist about that they'll have a heart attack.
Now you don't find any of Mujahideen(مجاهدين) dying because of heart attack,
but it's the problem is the lifestyle and Israf(إسراف),
a stationary lifestyle, you will develop diseases, no matter what you eating,
and with Israf(إسراف), you will develop diseases, no matter what you're eating.
Khalid Ibn Walid رضي الله عنه, he never survived on vegetables and fruits.
Nevertheless, he was Yani(يعني) strongest in the battlefield.
But because of their active lifestyle, they were healthy.
Anyway, I think maybe talk too much about this point but I'm just trying to say that we shouldn't blindly follow the fads
that come out in the west, every now and then once they tell you that vegetables are good for you,
sometimes they tell wine is good for you.
Just like for example when it comes to infants in America,
a while ago, they used to tell mothers.
You should have your newborn child sleep on their stomach, on the stomach, that's the most healthy way of sleeping,
but Rasool Allah ﷺ says that, that is the posture of the people of hellfire, the sleeping on the stomach.
Now, Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله) in America, they're telling women,
Don't have your child sleep on your stomach because that's a reason for sudden infant death. S.I.D.
You should have them either sleep on the side or the back.
So the thing is here. Do you follow the Sunnah(سنة) of Rasool Allah ﷺ
or do you follow what the every theory that comes up now and then.
One should trust in, what Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ says and the Sunnah(سنة) of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
and you can never go wrong with that.
And I've noticed this as among some brothers, they're making meat Haram(حرام) on themselves.
Actually one brother said that I have refrained completely from meat, I don't eat meat anymore.
I told him, why?
He said: Because it's not healthy.
And Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) did not eat meat and all that stuff.
Where did you get that from that Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) did not eat meat.?
In fact the staple of the people in Arabia was meat and bread, barley bread that was their food.
So don't make anything Haram(حرام) on yourself.
When Rasool Allah ﷺ make Asal(عسل), Honey Haram(حرام) on himself, the Ayaat(آيات) of Tahrim(تحريم) were revealed,
يَا أَيُّهَا النَّبِيُّ لِمَ تُحَرِّمُ مَا أَحَلَّ اللَّهُ لَكَ تَبْتَغِي مَرْضَاتَ أَزْوَاجِكَ
O Messenger of Allah, Why are you making what is Halal(حلال), Haram(حرام) on yourself.
These are Tayibaat(طيبات), all are Tayibaat(طيبات). One should just eat in moderation.
I'll read the exact wording of the Hadith(حديث).
Jabir Ibn Abdullah(جابربن عبدالله) narrates: We were sent on an expedition by the Messenger of Allah,
to raid the caravan owned by Quraish(قُرَيْشْ),
and he appointed Abu Obaidah(أبوعبيدة) as our leader,
the Messenger of Allah found nothing to provide us with except leather bags filled with dates and nothing else.
Abu Hurairah(ابوهريره) would then hand us one date each.
The narrator was asked what good would that be.
He said: We would eat it and then suck on the date seed.
In addition to drinking water that was the only food we would have for the whole day.
Then we would gather leaves of trees and soak them in water and eat them.
Then we headed for the direction of the coast.
We saw what appeared like a sand dune and to our surprise it was a whale.
Abu Obaidah(أبوعبيدة) at first said: It is dead, therefore it cannot be consumed.
He then said: But we are the messengers of the Messenger of Allah, and we are in the Cause of Allah,
and this is a necessity, so eat from it.
We stayed there for a whole month eating from it, until we grew fat,
and we were 300 in number,
we would collect oil from its eyes with buckets and cut from its flesh pieces as large as a bull.
Abu Obaidah(أبوعبيدة) had us fit 13 men in its eye socket.
He then had one of its rib bones fixed to the ground, like an arc.
Then he had the tallest camel with us, pass from under it, without the camel touching the bone.
We then picked up, dried meat, to carry with us to Madina.
When we told the Messenger of Allah, our story.
He said: That was sustenance, Allah sent for you.
Do you have any of that meat left with you to give me some.
We sent some to him and he ate from it.
This is in Sahih Muslim(صحيح ألمسلم).
Miscellaneous rewards for the Mujahid(مُجَاهِد), Allah says:
ما كانَ لِأَهلِ المَدينَةِ وَمَن حَولَهُم مِنَ الأَعرابِ أَن
أَن يَتَخَلَّفوا عَن رَسولِ اللَّهِ وَلا يَرغَبوا بِأَنفُسِهِم عَن نَفسِهِ ۚ
ذٰلِكَ بِأَنَّهُم لا يُصيبُهُم ظَمَأٌ وَلا نَصَبٌ وَلا
وَلا مَخمَصَةٌ في سَبيلِ اللَّهِ وَلا يَطَئونَ مَوطِئًا يَغيظُ الكُفّارَ
وَلا يَنالونَ مِن عَدُوٍّ نَيلًا إِلّا كُتِبَ لَهُم بِهِ عَمَلٌ صالِحٌ ۚ
إِنَّ اللَّهَ لا يُضيعُ أَجرَ المُحسِنينَ ۞
وَلا يُنفِقونَ نَفَقَةً صَغيرَةً وَلا كَبيرَةً وَلا
وَلا يَقطَعونَ وادِيًا إِلّا كُتِبَ لَهُم لِيَجزِيَهُمُ اللَّهُ أَحسَنَ ما كانوا يَعمَلونَ۞
That is because they are not afflicted by thirst or fatigue or hunger in the cause of Allah,
nor do they tread on any ground that enrages the disbelievers,
nor do they inflict upon an enemy any infliction, but that it is registered for them as righteous deed.
Indeed, Allah does not allow to be lost the reward of the doers of good.
Nor do they spend an expenditure, small or large, or cross a valley,
but that it is registered for them, that Allah may reward them for the best of what they were doing.
At-Toba(التوبة) Verse 120 and 121.
Abu Bakr Bin Abu Musa(أبوبكر بن أبوموسى) narrates:
I heard my father say that the Messenger of Allah said:
The gates of paradise are lying under the swords.
A poor man with rags stood up and said:
O, Abu Musa(أبوموسى), Did you hear that from the Messenger of Allah.?
My father said: Yes!
The man went back to his company and told them, I give you my Salam(سلام).
He then broke his sword, sheath and marched towards the enemy striking them with a sword until he was killed.
So this is Abu Musa Al-Ash'ari(أبوموسى ألأشعري) speaking in a mosque,
he said: That Jannah(جنة) is under the shade of swords.
So this man heard that and he said: Did you hear this from Rasool Ullah.?
Abu Musa(أبوموسى) said: Yes!
He went and fought, until he was killed.
What does Ibn Daqeeq Al-Eid(إبن دقيق ألعيد) say about this Hadith(حديث)?
He said:
The statement that the gates of paradise are lying under the swords,
would mean that paradise is attained through the swords of the Mujahideen(مجاهدين),
and using the sword is necessary to get paradise and to open its gates,
as if the sword is the key to Jannah(جنة).
The Messenger of Allah said: Whoever fights in the cause of Allah, the time it takes to milk a camel is granted paradise.
And this is in Ahmed(أحمد), Abu Daud(أبوداؤد), At-Tirmidhi(ألتِّرمِذِيْ), Ibn Majah(إبن ماجه) and Ibn Habban(إبن حَبَّان).
Abu Hurairah(ابوهريره) narrated the Messenger of Allah said:
The trials and tribulations are on their way, trials like pieces of a dark night,
the safest from them would be a man living on the peaks of mountains, living off his flock of sheep
or a man mounting his horse, living off his sword.
Al-Hakim(ألحاكم).
So in the times of Fitan(فتن), only two people will be safe.
The Mujahid(مُجَاهِد), who is riding hs horse fighting Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله),
and the one who avoids all of the Fitan(فتن) and goes and lives off his sheep, the peaks of mountains.
Everyone else will be consumed by the Fitnah(فِتْنَه).
Subura(صَبُورا) narrated, I heard the Messenger of Allah say:
Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ) has intercepted the son of Adam(آدم) on his path towards Islam and told him.
Are you going to become Muslim, and leave your heritage and the religion of your forefathers.
But the son of Adam(آدم) disobeyed him and became a Muslim and was forgiven.
Then Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ) sat for him, on his path to Hijrah(هجرة) and told him:
Will you make Hijrah(هجرة) and leave behind your home and land.?
He disobeyed him and made Hijrah(هجرة).
He then sat for him on his path towards Jihad(جهاد) and told him:
Are you going to fight when it's an exhaustion of yourself, and your wealth,
you would go to kill, and you would be killed, and then your wife would be taken and the wealth divided,
the son of Adam(آدم) disobeyed him and went on Jihad(جهاد),
the Messenger of Allah, then said:
Whoever does that, it is incumbent upon Allah to admit him to paradise.
Or if he dies by his animals striking him, he would go to paradise.
So Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ) keeps on interrupting you.
When you become Muslim, when you make Hijrah(هجرة), and anyone you make Jihad(جهاد).
Now brothers: Pay close attention to this statement.
Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) said: If I were to marry a beautiful woman, whom I love,
or if I were given the good news of having a newborn son.
It is less beloved and dear to my heart, than to be in a cold icy night in an army,
waiting to meet the enemy, the next morning.
I advise you to go on Jihad(جهاد).
These were the words of Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) before he died.
Now, brother, if I were to marry a beautiful woman whom I love,
or if I were given the good news of having a newborn son.
It is less beloved and dear to my heart, than to be in a cold icy night, in an army waiting to meet the enemy, the next morning,
I advise you to go on Jihad(جهاد).
The brothers who are married, if you can go back to the memory of the day you got married.
If you love your wife and you got married.
Think about that.
The brothers who have children. Think about the day when you had your new firstborn.
Think about the day you're given the news of having a newborn child.
These are days that you cannot forget.
These are events that make you the happiest on that day, you feel the top of the world.
These are natural human feelings.
Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) is saying: If I'm to marry a woman whom I love, and she's beautiful.
Or if I'm given the news of having a newborn son.
That is less dear to my heart, then spending a night in a tent and it's a very cold icy, windy night
and the next day in the morning I'm going to meet my enemy.
Do you see how much love that Khalid Ibn Walid رضي الله عنه had for Jihad(جهاد) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله),
for you to love, Jihad(جهاد) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله), and not just Jihad(جهاد), you're in the middle of it.
And it's a cold, icy windy night.
Now, Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) is not a soldier in the army.
And by just being a soldier in the moment is tantalizing itself,
because you know that the next day you might not be living anymore.
You know that the next day you might be injured and in those days injuries, you know there's no anesthesia.
Nusayba Bint  Ka'ab(نُصيبة بنت كعب), who fought on Al-Yamamah(أليمامة), she said:
I left with 12 injuries in my body, and Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) was so kind and nice with us, Ansaar(ألأنْصَار).
He appointed a physician to me, to come and take care of my wounds, and he would pour on my wounds boiling oil.
And the pain and suffering of the healing process was even worse than the injury itself.
Because in those days, there's no anesthesia, there's no anti bacteria so what they would use is boiling oil.
What it does is? Its seals the injury, and it kills the infection.
Now, some people before they go to the dentist for days they're thinking about that poking of the needle.
Just poking of needle.
And it's an anesthesia needle, it is to take away the pain that will come after it,
and they would think about it for days.
The Sahabah(صحابه) knew very well where they're getting themselves into,
Nusayba Bint  Ka'ab(نُصيبة بنت كعب), she knew very well, the suffering and pain that she could get,
when she goes on fight, I mean in those days, I mean, swords and arrows and spears are piercing your body.
So the soldier, not Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) the leader, the soldier by just thinking,
imagine the pressure they're under you know tomorrow I might be killed, tomorrow I might be injured,
tomorrow I might be handicapped.
So they're under so much tension.
Now Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) is not soldier, Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد), is leader of the army.
And as the leader of the Army, you are responsible for whatever happens the next day.
And the Mujahideen(مجاهدين) they love each other and the leader if he makes a mistake
and some of his brothers died because of that will feel a lot of pain.
And he is responsible for the victory or loss that would happen the next day.
It's Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) was held responsible for that.
So think about the mental pressure, the psychological pressure he is going through.
And in those days, I mean the Muslims, they would take defeat very seriously, I mean they wouldn't accept it.
Now Muslims are desensitized, it doesn't make a difference anymore but in those days, it was a serious thing.
I mean when Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) was appointed leader in Mu'tah(مَؤتَة) and he retreated,
and he went into Madina what happened.?
I mean, look at the spirit that the kids had in Madina,
those kids would go and throw rocks at the army, and they say,
أنتم الفراغون
You are the ones, who ran away.
Kids of today who are playing Playstation have no idea what's going around in the world
but in those days, even the children knew what was happening.
And imagine how painful it is for an army to come in and the kids are pelting you with rocks.
The kids of Madina are saying,
أنتم الفراغون
You are the ones who ran away from battle.
It wasn't remain until Rasool Allah ﷺ came for their defense and said,
بل هم القراهون
But they are the ones, who are retreating to attack again.
Otherwise those kids would have given them a very hard time.
This also shows you Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله), that the Spirit that existed in Madina,
spirit of Jihad(جهاد), even the kids were involved in it.
Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد), is going through all of that pressure, he can't sleep the night, he has to plan.
He loves that more than marrying a beautiful woman that he loves,
or having a newborn child.
That is the love of Jihad(جهاد) that's on a different level.
Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد), he said, and this is narrated by Ibn-e-Asakir(إبن عساكر).
I was prevented a lot of recitation of Qur'an because of my preoccupation, in Jihad(جهاد).
حرمنن جهاد من تلاوت كثير من القرآن
In fact, it is said that, when he would lead the Salah(صلاة), because the Ameer(أمير) of the army would lead the Salah(صلاة),
he will start in one Surah(سورة) and finish in another. He would confuse the Ayaat(آيات).
But then he said: The reason is because I'm preoccupied with Jihad(جهاد) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله).
References to the preference of Jihad(جهاد) over Hajj(حَجْ).
Allah Ho Akbar(الله اكبر), listen to what Ibn Umar(إبن عُمَر) says and this narrated by Ibn Al-Mubarak(إبن المبارك),
and Ibn Abi Shaibah(إبن أبي شعيبة), and the narration is authentic.
Abdullah Ibn Umar(عبدالله ابن عمر) said:
One trip on Jihad(جهاد) is better than 50 Hajj(حَجْ).
This is Sahih(صحيح) narration, one trip on Jihad(جهاد) is better than 50 Hajj(حَجْ).
Dhirar Ibn Amr(ضرارإبن عمرو) said:
I have spent a very long time in Jihad(جهاد) and my heart was longing to Hajj(حَجْ).
I made my preparations to go, and then went to greet my brothers.
I visited Is'haq Ibn Abi Farwah(إسحاق إبن أبي فروة), one of the scholars, to give him farewell.
He asked me: Where are you going?
I said: I'm going to Hajj(حَجْ).
He said: Has your opinion on Jihad(جهاد) changed or what?
Did your opinion on Jihad(جهاد) changed?
He said: No! It's just that I have been here on Jihad(جهاد) for a long time.
Now I was longing for Hajj(حَجْ) and visiting the house of Allah,
you know, if you visited the house of Allah once you become addicted to it, you become hooked for life.
There's something about the house of Allah that attracts the hearts of the believer.
And that is because of the Dua(دُعَا) of Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم).
فَاجْعَلْ أَفْئِدَةً مِنَ النَّاسِ تَهْوِي إِلَيْهِمْ
Make the hearts of people rush towards the house of Allah.
Ibrahim عليه السّلام was told by Allah
أذن في الناس بالحج
Call the people to Hajj(حَجْ), make Adhan(آذَان), called the people to Hajj(حَجْ).
When he finished building the house of Allah, there was nobody living there.
It was empty.
And Allah is telling him to invite the people to Hajj(حَجْ), Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) said:
Oh Allah, my voice is weak, and it cannot reach the people, Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ told him,
عليك ندا وعلينا عجابة
You will make the invitation, and we will convey it.
So now that call of Ibrahim عليه السّلام is being conveyed in every year by millions of Muslims, coming from every corner of the globe.
And as soon as you see the house of Allah once when you leave, you become homesick.
When you go back home, you become homesick because Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ says:
وَإِذْ جَعَلْنَا الْبَيْتَ مَثَابَةً لِّلنَّاسِ
Masaba(مَثَابَةً) means something that you want to go back to frequently.
The house is Masaba(مَثَابَةً), you want to visit it again and again and again.
You leave you go back home, you feel homesick to the house of Allah.
It was said that Christian missionaries were working in Indonesia very hard to convert the people to Christianity.
So after some very hard work,
they were able to convince this man, this old man to become Christian, and they only did so
after they promised him that we will fulfill your wish, you make a wish. We will do it for you.
So when he became Christian they said: What's your wish. He said: To make Hajj(حَجْ).
This is an Indonesian see the connection that the people have to the house of Allah, even though they're miles and miles away.
You know, for the Indonesian Hajji(حجَّي) before it used to be an entire year to make Hajj(حَجْ),
six months going and six months coming back.
It wasn't an easy thing. Nevertheless, they would go to Hajj(حَجْ).
So this man is in Jihad(جهاد) and now he wants to go to the house of Allah, He said:
It's been a long time, I haven't seen the house of Allah I want to go.
He said: No, it's just that I have been here on Jihad(جهاد) for a long time,
and I was longing for Hajj(حَجْ) visiting the house of Allah.
He told me: O Dharar(ضرار), you should not do what you love, but you should do what Allah loves
and see Brothers its a very important thing.
You don't do what you want to do but you do what Allah wants you to do.
We always go with what our whims tell us, tell us, and I'm talking about Ibadaat(عبادات).
What if Allah has puts you in a Saghra(ثغرة), Allah has put you in a certain position.
Don't allow Islam to be attacked from that position.
It is your responsibility to man that post
and not allow Islam to be attacked from where you are appointed
and don't change that post just because you don't feel like doing it do what pleases Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
So he told him: You should not do what you love, but you should do what Allah loves.
O Dharar(ضرار), Don't you know that the Messenger of Allah only made Hajj(حَجْ) once,
but then he spent his life fighting in Jihad(جهاد) until he met Allah.
O Dharar(ضرار), if you make Hajj(حَجْ), then you are rewarded for your Hajj(حَجْ) and Umrah(عمرة).
But if you are posted in Jihad(جهاد) or fighting and protecting the backs of Muslims,
then if the house is visited by 100,000 pilgrims,
or whatever number you would be getting the reward of every one of their Hajj(حَجْ)
and the Hajj(حَجْ) of every believing man or woman, until the day of judgment.
Because whoever protects the believers is like the one who protects them,
from the time of Adam(آدم) until the Day of Judgment.
These people are only making Hajj(حَجْ), because you are protecting them.
Therefore you will have a share in every Hajj(حَجْ) that they make.
And then he says,: You are also rewarded for fighting the non believers from the day of Adam(آدم), until the day of judgment,
because whoever fights them today is like the one, who fights them from the day Adam(آدم) was created,
until the day of judgment.
You are also rewarded for every letter revealed in the Torah(تولراة), gospel and Qur'an
because you are fighting to protect the light of Allah, from being extinguished.
O Dharar Bin Amr(ضراربن عمرو),
Don't you know that there is no one closer to the status of prophethood, than the scholars of the Mujahideen(مجاهدين).
I said: And how's that.
He said, because the scholars are the ones, who fulfill the role of the prophets in guiding others to the truth,
and teaching it to them.
While the Mujahideen(مجاهدين), are the ones, who fight for what the prophets have brought
and strive to make the word of Allah, the highest and the word of the non believers, the lowest.
Dharar(ضرار) said: I decided to give up Hajj(حَجْ) and remain in Jihad(جهاد), until I die and meet Allah.
Tayeb(طيِّب),
صَلَّى الله عَلى سَيَّدِنَا محمد وَعَلى اَلِهِ وَ صَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ
If you have any questions.
We should gear everything that we do towards the service of religion.
And if the venue of Jihad(جهاد) is not open today it will be open tomorrow.
Therefore, no time is wasted.
Because the preparation for Jihad(جهاد) is Jihad(جهاد). And
مال يتم الواجب ، إلَّا به فهو واجب
The things that lead to something that is wajib(واجب) are also wajib(واجب).
If the wajib(واجب) is based on some prerequisites, those prerequisites become wajib(واجب).
So, we don't have any time to waste or spare.
We need the Eeman(ايمان) preparation, financial preparation, physical preparation, mental preparation.
You know to get yourself into the mental status of willing to leave.
Leave behind everything.
That in itself takes some preparation to get yourself to that state, where, when the call of
حيَّ على الجهاد
comes, I'm immediately going to respond to it.
Because in the time of Fitan(فتن) and when the Fitnah(فِتْنَه) hits.
If you are not ready for it from before you cannot be ready for it after there's no time for preparation after it.
To give an extreme example with Dajjal(دجال). Rasool Allah ﷺ says:
لَا يَنْفَعُ نَفْسًا إِيمَانُهَا لَمْ تَكُنْ آمَنَتْ مِنْ قَبْلُ أَوْ كَسَبَتْ فِي إِيمَانِهَا خَيْرًا
And he is narrating, an Ayah(آية) in Qur'an.
At that time, no soul will benefit if it did not already benefit from its Eeman(ايمان) before.
So when the Dajjal(دجال) comes, you cannot say: I'm going to prepare for him now.
If you weren't already ready. You failed.
So, when the call comes in time of fittan(فتن) a person already needs to be ready, to face the test
because there is no time for preparation for the test and you cannot cram it, the evening before.
Therefore, there's a lot to be done, and brothers should not be edgy or in a hurry and to hasten things.
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ has a plan and the Rayah(راية) of Jihad(جهاد) will never stop.
If it stops in one place, Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ opens it somewhere else.
But the problem is that brothers waste a lot of time and when it's open, they're not ready for it.
Yahya bin Maeen(يحي بن معين) and Ahmed Bin Hanbal(أحمد بن حنبل) and some other scholars say
that Taifa-Al-Mansoorah(طائفة المنصورة) are Ahl-Ul-Hadith(أهل الحديث) that people of Hadith(حديث).
What is meant by the people of Hadith.?
It means that they are the people who are the closest to following the Sunnah(سنة) of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
It is the people who emphasize on the Sunnah(سنة) of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
that is the Taifah(طائفة), it doesn't necessarily mean scholars of Hadith(حديث).
See At-Taifah(ألطائفة) is sometimes when it says Ahl-Ul-Hadith(أهل الحديث)
we misinterpret it because there's a group named Ahl-Ul-Hadith(أهل الحديث) and the scholars of Hadith(حديث)
we misinterpret the meaning of Ahl-Ul-Hadith(أهل الحديث) to mean scholars of Hadith(حديث).
Does that mean that scholars of Fiqh(فقه) are not Taifah(طائفة), or the Tafseer(تفسير)
and how comes it's scholars Hadith(حديث).
So, that's not the right understanding of what Ahl-Ul-Hadith(أهل الحديث) means.
Ahl-Ul-Hadith(أهل الحديث) means the people of Hadith(حديث),
the people who are following the Hadith(حديث) of Rasool Allah ﷺ and trying to emulate his way in their lives,
which makes the Mujahideen(مجاهدين), the closest to this definition,
because they are the ones, who are trying their best to follow the Sunnah(سنة) Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Therefore you would find that it's very rare to find among Al-Mujahideen(مجاهدين), people have problems with Sunnah(سنة).
The whole lifestyle of Jihad(جهاد) brings you closer to the Sunnah(سنة) of Rasool Allah ﷺ and wanting to be like Rasool Allah ﷺ.
If you wanted to be like Rasool Allah ﷺ and the thing that preoccupied Rasool Allah ﷺ for his entire stay in Madina,
why wouldn't you want to be like him in the way he looked,
or the way he ate, or the issues that are much simpler.
So Ahl-Ul-Hadith(أهل الحديث) here is the people, who are trying to follow the way of Rasool Allah ﷺ in their life.
That's what is meant by Ahl-Ul-Hadith(أهل الحديث).
So it doesn't really change the time, it's same.